<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>Nikos Roussos</author>
  <title>nikos.roussos &bull; reading</title>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Making things distributed is hard</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/03/12/making-things-distributed-is-hard/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>One of the most interesting rants I have ever read, by Maciej Cegłowski.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Technology concentrates power.</p>
<p>In the 90's, it looked like the Internet might be an exception, that it could be a decentralizing, democratizing force. No one controlled it, no one designed it, it was just kind of assembling itself in an appealing, anarchic way. The companies that first tried to centralize the Internet, like AOL and Microsoft, failed risibly. And open source looked ready to slay any dragon.</p>
<p>But those days are gone. We've centralized the bejesus out of the Internet now. There's <a href="http://www.lycos.com/">one search engine</a> (plus the one no one uses), <a href="http://myspace.com/">one social network</a> (plus the one no one uses), one Twitter. We use one ad network, one analytics suite. Anywhere you look online, one or two giant American companies utterly dominate the field.</p>
<p>And there's the cloud. What a brilliant name! The cloud is the future of online computing, a friendly, fluffy abstraction that we will all ascend into, swaddled in light. But really the cloud is just a large mess of servers somewhere, the property of one American company (plus the clouds no one uses).</p>
<p>Orwell imagined a world with a <a href="http://www.theorwellreader.com/excerpt.shtml">telescreen in every room</a>, always on, always connected, always monitored. An <a href="http://au.ign.com/wikis/xbox-one/Xbox_One_Kinect">Xbox One</a> vision of dystopia.</p>
<p>But we've done him one better. Nearly everyone here carries in their pocket a tracking device that knows where you are, who you talk to, what you look at, all these intimate details of your life, and sedulously reports them to private servers where the data is stored in perpetuity.</p>
<p>I know I sound like a conspiracy nut framing it like this. I'm not saying we live in an Orwellian nightmare. I love New Zealand! But we have the technology.</p>
<p>When I was in grade school, they used to scare us with something called the permanent record. If you threw a spitball at your friend, it would go in your permanent record, and prevent you getting a good job, or marrying well, until eventually you'd die young and friendless and be buried outside the churchyard wall.</p>
<p>What a relief when we found out that the permanent record was a fiction. Except now we've gone and implemented the damned thing. Each of us leaves an indelible, comet-like trail across the Internet that cannot be erased and that we're not even allowed to see.</p>
<p>The things we really care about seem to disappear from the Internet immediately, but post a stupid YouTube comment (now linked to your real identity) and it will live forever.</p>
<p>And we have to track all this stuff, because the economic basis of today's web is advertising, or the promise of future advertising. The only way we can convince investors to keep the money flowing is by keeping the most detailed records possible, tied to people's real identities. Apart from a few corners of anonymity, which not by accident are the <a href="http://chrishateswriting.com/post/76431353368/the-anonymity-i-know">most culturally vibrant parts</a> of the Internet, everything is tracked and has to be tracked or the edifice collapses.</p>
<p>What upsets me isn't that we created this centralized version of the Internet based on permanent surveillance.</p>
<p>What upsets me, what really gets my goat, is that we did it because it was the easiest thing to do. There was no design, forethought, or analysis involved. No one said "hey, this sounds like a great world to live in, let's make it". It happened because we couldn't be bothered.</p>
<p>Making things ephemeral is hard.</p>
<p>Making things distributed is hard.</p>
<p>Making things anonymous is hard.</p>
<p>Coming up with a sane business model is really hard—I get tired just thinking about it.</p>
<p>So let's take people's data, throw it on a server, link it to their Facebook profiles, keep it forever, and if we can't raise another round of venture funding we'll just slap Google ads on the thing.</p>
<p>"High five, Chad!"</p>
<p>"High five, bro!"</p>
<p>That is the design process that went into building the Internet of 2014.</p>
<p>And of course now we are shocked—shocked!—when, for example, the Ukrainian government uses cell tower data to send scary text messages to protesters in Kiev, in order to try to keep them off the streets. Bad people are using the global surveillance system we built to do something mean! Holy crap! Who could have imagined this?</p>
<p>Or when we learn that the American government is reading the email that you send unencrypted to the ad-supported mail service in another country where it gets archived forever. Inconceivable!</p>
<p>I'm not saying these abuses aren't serious. But they're the opposite of surprising. People will always abuse power. That's not a new insight. There are cuneiform tablets complaining about it. Yet here we are in 2014, startled because unscrupulous people have started to use the powerful tools we created for them.</p>
<p>We put so much care into making the Internet resilient from technical failures, but make no effort to make it resilient to political failure. We treat freedom and the rule of law like inexhaustible natural resources, rather than the fragile and precious treasures that they are.</p>
<p>And now, of course, it's time to make the Internet of Things, where we will connect everything to everything else, and build cool apps on top, and nothing can possibly go wrong. </p>
<p>Not long ago before I flew here, Google announced it was acquiring Nest, a luxury thermostat maker. I never thought I would use those two words together. Nest has sensors that detect who is in a room and when, so naturally there was concern that Google would now learn all this extra information about you, and know how hot your house is.</p>
<p>Google quickly deployed the Nest CEO, who promised that there would be safeguards and a privacy policy, and all kinds limits to make sure everything stayed kosher. And I have no reason to disbelieve the guy.</p>
<p>But I shouldn't need his word, or Google's corporate motto, or Magna Carta, or the <a href="http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/politics/treaty/the-treaty-in-brief">Treaty of Waitangi</a> to protect me from my thermostat. My old thermostat wasn't that scary! It was too dumb to snitch. And no one could hear it scream.</p>
<p>This new thermostat, on the other hand, has lawyers, PR people, a privacy policy, it's off writing blog posts somewhere, possibly eating my leftover pizza. It more like a sketchy roommate than a thermostat.</p>
<p>Let me make it clear what I'm worried about here. I'm not afraid of my appliances. I'm not afraid that Google is going to send me to the Googlag to mine bitcoins.</p>
<p>Nor am I afraid of a Greater New Zealand, grown drunk with electronic surveillance, aggressively expanding to control the Pacific Rim. That might be a nice change! If it happens, I will be waiting on the docks of San Francisco, bearing a basket of avocados, ready to welcome our Kiwi overlords.</p>
<p>What I'm afraid of is the society we already live in. Where people like you and me, if we stay inside the lines, can enjoy lives of comfort and relative ease, but God help anyone who is declared out of bounds. Those people will feel the full might of the high-tech modern state.</p>
<p>Consider your neighbors across the Tasman, stewards of an empty continent, who have <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Solution">set up internment camps in the remotest parts of the Pacific</a> for fear that a few thousand indigent people might come in on boats, take low-wage jobs, and thereby destroy their society.</p>
<p>Or the country I live in, where we have a bipartisan consensus that the only way to preserve our freedom is to fly remote controlled planes that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drone_attacks_in_Pakistan#Civilian_casualties">occasionally drop bombs on children</a>. It's <a href="http://classiclit.about.com/od/brotherskaramazov/a/aa_brothersqut.htm">straight out of Dostoevski</a>.</p>
<p>Except Dostoevski needed a doorstop of a book to grapple with the question: “Is it ever acceptable for innocents to suffer for the greater good?” And the Americans, a more practical people, have answered that in two words: “Of course!”</p>
<p>Erika Hall in <a href="http://www.webstock.org.nz/14/programme/presentations/#hall">her talk yesterday</a> wondered what Mao or Stalin could have done with the resources of the modern Internet. It's a good question. If you look at the history of the KGB or Stasi, they consumed enormous resources just maintaining and cross-referencing their mountains of paperwork. There's a throwaway line in Huxley's Brave New World where he mentions "800 cubic meters of card catalogs" in the eugenic baby factory. Imagine what Stalin could have done with a decent MySQL server.</p>
<p>We haven't seen yet what a truly bad government is capable of doing with modern information technology. What the good ones get up to is terrifying enough.</p>
<p>I'm not saying we can't have the fun next-generation Internet, where everyone wears stupid goggles and has profound conversations with their refrigerator. I'm just saying we can't slap it together like we've been doing so far and expect everything to work itself out.</p>
<p>The good news is, it's a design problem! You're all designers here - we can make it fun! We can build an Internet that's distributed, resilient, irritating to governments everywhere, and free in the best sense of the word, like we dreamed of in the 90's. But it will take effort and determination. It will mean scrapping permanent mass surveillance as a business model, which is going to hurt. It will mean pushing laws through a sclerotic legal system. There will have to be some nagging.</p>
<p>But if we don't design this Internet, if we just continue to build it out, then eventually it will attract some remarkable, visionary people. And we're not going to like them, and it's not going to matter.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can read the <a href="https://static.pinboard.in/webstock_2014.htm">full transcript</a> of the presentation (which actually is about the life of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A9on_Theremin">Lev Sergeyevich Termen</a>).</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-03-12 14:41:16</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Παραμύθια</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2010/05/12/paramithia/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/4583853426/"><img alt="just a break" src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4019/4583853426_6e87ddbc7c.jpg" /></a></p>
<p>"Παραμύθια";... Α λοιπόν θα σας πω κι ένα παραμύθι να ξεκουραστείτε! Μια φορά κι ένα καιρό οι κλέφτες της πρώτης πολιτείας του κόσμου, αφού πλουτίσανε αρκετά, αποφασίσανε να ταχτοποιήσουνε τη ζωή τους. Μπλοκάρανε το λοιπόν τους φτωχούς της πολιτείας κι αφού τους μαζώξανε στην πλατεία τους είπανε: "Ψηλά τα χέρια! Θέλουμε το καλό σας. Δεν θα σας πάρουμε τα φτυάρια, τους κασμάδες, τα σκεπάρνια, τα δισάκια και τα ζεμπίλια σας με το ψωμοτύρι, τα τρύπια σας πουκάμισα με τις ψείρες και τις απάτωτες καλύβες σας, που κάνουνε νερά, σαν βρέχει. Είσαστε ελεύθεροι! - (ψηλά τα χέρια!). Ελεύθεροι να ζείτε κατά το κέφι σας, να κερδίζετε, να κάνετε κομπόδεμα, να μεθάτε, να χορεύεται, να γεννοβολάτε και να πεθαίνετε. Εμείς θα σας μαθαίνουμε τις... αλήθειες! Θα σας δώσουμε πλούσια φαντασία κι αισθαντική καρδιά, θα σας δώσουμε κι αθάνατη ψυχή. Κι όποιος από σας γουστάρει, θα μπορεί να γράφει ποιήματα, να σκαρώνει θεωρίες και να δοξάζεται! Ο κυρίαρχος λαός θα 'σαστε εσείς! Εμείς μονάχα θα σας καμαρώνουμε. Θα φροντίζουμε για την ασφάλεια της ζωής, της τιμής και της περιουσίας σας - μ' ένα λόγο για την ελευθερίας σας. Σεις θα δουλεύετε, κατά πως θέλετε κι ό,τι θέλετε κι όποτε θέλετε. Εμείς θα σας δίνουμε δουλειά, φτάνει να βρίσκεται, και σεις θα μας δίνετε τα κόπια σας. Και για να μη θαρρέψετε πως σας αδικούμε, θα πλερώνουμε κι εμείς το ίδιο δόσιμο στο Κράτος, - στον εαυτό μας!</p>
<p>Κι εσείς κι εμείς θα 'χουμε πάνω απ' τα κεφάλια μας τους ίδιους θεούς, που θα προστάζουν εσάς να δουλεύετε και να μην τρώτε κι εμάς να καθόμαστε και να τρώμε. Κι εμείς κι εσείς θα έχουμε πάνω απ' τα κεφάλια μας τους ίδιους νόμους, που εμείς θα σας τους δίνουμε κι εσείς θα τους ψηφίζετε σαν βουλευτάδες και θα τους εφαρμόζετε σαν δικαστάδες ενάντια στον εαυτό σας. Και για να μην πλακώνουν απ' άλλες στεριές και θάλασσες κουρσάροι και κλέφτες ν' αρπάζουνε το υστέρημα σας και να παίρνουνε σκλάβους κι εσάς και τις γυναίκες σας και τα παιδιά σας, θα σας αρματώνουμε, θα σας γυμνάζουμε, για να μπορείτε να διαφεντεύετε τους θεούς σας, τον εαυτό σας κι εμάς, δηλαδή την πατρίδα. Να σκοτώνεστε σεις και να ζούμε εμείς. Κι επειδή μοναχοί σας δεν θα μπορούσατε να σκεφτείτε το συμφέρον σας και να φυλάξετε τον εαυτό σας, θα σας αναγκάζουμε με το ζόρι (ψηλά τα χέρια!). Ένα πράμα μονάχα σας απαγορεύουμε: να κλέβει ο ένας τον άλλον. Γιατί μπορεί να κλέψετε κι εμάς"</p>
<p><em>~ Κ. Βάρναλης: "η αληθινή απολογία του Σωκράτη"</em></p></content>
      <pubDate>2010-05-12 19:14:22</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>νωθρότητα</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2010/03/08/nothrotita/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>«Εδώ όλα είναι αποτέλεσμα νωθρότητας, και τα κακά και τα καλά. Όλα σπορρέουν από την αριστοκρατική, χαριτωμένη, μορφωμένη, πεισματάρικη νωθρότητα! Δεν ξέρουμε να ζούμε από το μόχθο μας. Και, πώς μας προέκυψε το ότι ορισμένοι ασχολούνται τώρα με κάποια "αναδειχθείσα" κοινή γνώμη, έτσι ξαφνικά; Είναι δυνατόν να μην καταλαβαίνουν ότι για να διαμορφώσεις άποψη χρειάζεται πριν απ' όλα να μοχθήσεις, προσωπικά, με ατομική πρωτοβουλία, με ατομική δράση! Χάρισμα τίποτε και ποτέ δεν δίνεται. Αν μοχθήσουμε, άποψη για εμάς θα έχουν μόνο αυτοί που δούλευαν αντί για μας μέχρι τώρα, δηλαδή η Ευρώπη ως συνήθως, οι Γερμανοί ως συνήθως, αυτοί που είναι δάσκαλοι μας, δηλαδή, διακόσια χρόνια τώρα.»
<em>~ Φ. Ντοστογιέφσκι, Δαιμονισμένοι</em></p></content>
      <pubDate>2010-03-08 21:15:02</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>ο μύθος της "ελεύθερης αγοράς"</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2010/02/15/o-mithos-tis-eleftheris-agoras/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>«(...) Η "ελεύθερη αγορά" όμως δεν είναι παρά ένας μύθος των νεοφιλελεύθερων. Η παρεμβατικότητα και η ρυθμιστική πολιτική του κράτους είναι καθοριστική για την εξσφάλιση της μεγαλύτερης δυνατής ισορροπίας και εν τέλει την λειτουργία και την αποτελεσματικότητα της αγοράς. Εκ φύσεως η αγορά συμπεριφέρεται απρόβλεπτα, και προκειμένου να μην οδηγηθεί στον αυτο-στραγγαλισμό της από τον εξοντωτικό ανταγωνισμό και τις μονοπωλειακές τάσεις του κεφαλαίου, πρέπει να αποδοθεί στο κράτος ο ρόλος του νομοθέτη, που με την διακριτική παρέμβασή του φροντίζει να διατηρεί η "ελεύθερη αγορά" την αυτονομία της - τουλάχιστον ως καταστατική μυθολογία της αέναης οικονομικής ανάπτυξης και της κοινωνικής προόδου του κράτους και της κοινωνίας. Το κράτος εξασφαλίζει και διαμορφώνει τις συνθήκες για την ανάπτυξη κάθε οικονομικής δραστηριότητας και προσφέρει ένα μίνιμουμ διασφάλισης από κάθε είδος κινδύνων. Χωρίς αυτό το πλαίσιο καμία έννοια "φιλελεύθερης" οικονομίας δεν θα ήταν εφικτή - και αυτό το γνωρίζει και ο πρωτοετής φοιτητής Οικονομικών, πόσο μάλλον οι "φωτισμένοι" ιδεολόγοι του νεοφιλελευθερισμού ή οι μάνατζερ των πολυεθνικών. (...)»
_~ απ' το editorial του <a href="http://futura-blog.blogspot.com/">futura</a> - τεύχος 11 _</p>
<p>«Όποιος πιστεύει ότι η εκθετική ανάπτυξη μπορεί να συνεχίζεται για πάντα σε ένα πεπερασμένο κόσμο είναι είτε τρελός είτε οικονομολόγος»
_~ K. Boulding (οικονομολόγος) _</p></content>
      <pubDate>2010-02-15 20:57:21</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>πατριώτες</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2009/10/28/patriotes/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>«Ποιοι είναι αυτοί;», ρωτάω κάποιον πλάι μου.<br />
«Ποιοι;», λέει. «Αυτοί που πίνουν στο μπουφέ.»<br />
«Δεν τους ξέρετε; Εκ των πρώτων της κοινωνίας... Μέτοχοι και διευθυντές, σύμβουλοι, πρόεδροι φιλανθρωπικών ιδρυμάτων.»<br />
«Θα είναι πολύ συνεπείς.», λέω. «Θα ναι "κύριοι". Συμβόλαιο θα είναι λόγος της τιμής τους.»<br />
«Βέβαια...», μου λέει. «Και πλούτισαν χάρις σ' όλα αυτά τα προσόντα τους. Η <em>πατρίδα</em> είναι αυτοί.»<br />
(Κι οι <em>πατριώτες</em> εμείς), συλλογίστηκα.</p>
<p>~ γ. σκαρίμπας: "το βατερλώ δύο γελοίων"</p></content>
      <pubDate>2009-10-28 11:07:31</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>ηλιοθεραπεία</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2009/05/26/iliotherapia/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><img alt="παμπούδη" src="pampudi.jpg" /></p>
<p>λάτρεψα την <a href="http://www.servitoros.gr/education/view.php/18/346/">παυλίνα παμπούδη</a> απ' τα "15 1/2 κάπως περίεργα παραμύθια" (θα ποστάρω προσεχώς κάποιο παραμύθι της). προς το παρόν ένα ποίημα της.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ηλιοθεραπεία κάνουν
η Ηρώ κι ο Ηρακλής
ήρθε ήλιος, ήρθε ήλιος
μες στη μέση της αυλής,
ήρθε κι ο ηλεκτρολόγος
δίχως να υπάρχει λόγος!</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>~ παυλίνα παμπούδη</em></p></content>
      <pubDate>2009-05-26 00:07:53</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>book meme</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2008/11/15/book-meme/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>i read it somewhere and i liked the idea :) </p>
<ul>
<li>grab the nearest book.</li>
<li>open it to page 56.</li>
<li>find the fifth sentence.</li>
<li>post the text of the sentence in your journal along with these instructions.</li>
<li>don’t dig for your favorite book, the cool book, or the intellectual one: pick the CLOSEST.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>so here is my choice: "stage two: an enzyme tightening the molecule's hexagonal ring into a pentagon, transforming the spare vertex into a protruding cluster, more exposed and reactive than before."
<em>~ from "permutation city" by greg egan</em></p>
</blockquote></content>
      <pubDate>2008-11-15 11:46:10</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>exit the system</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2007/02/05/exit-the-system/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>«It is an inherit property of intelligence that it can jump out of the task which it is performing, and survey what it has done; it is always looking for, and often finding, patterns. Now I said that an intelligence can jump out of its task, but that does not mean that it always will. However, a little prompting will often suffice. For example, a human being who is reading a book may grow sleepy. Instead of continuing to read until the book is finished, he is just as likely to put the book aside and turn off the light. He has stepped "out of the system" and yet it seems the most natural thing in the world to us.</p>
<p>Or, suppose person A is watching television when person B comes in the room, and shows evident displeasure with the situation. Person A may think he understands the problem, and try to remedy it by exiting the present system (the television program), and flipping the channel knob, looking for a better show. Person B may have a more radical concept of what it is to "exit the system" - namely to turn the television off! Of course, there are cases where only a rare individual will have the vision to perceive a system which governs many peoples' lives, a system which had never before even been recognised as a system; then such people often devote their lives to convincing other people that the system really is there, and that it ought to be exited from!»</p>
<p><em>~ d. hofstadter ("<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del%2C_Escher%2C_Bach">godel, escher, bach</a>" - 1979)</em></p>
<p>5 years before <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuromancer">neuromancer</a>, 10 years before <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghost_in_the_Shell_(manga)">ghost in the shell</a>, 20 years before <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Matrix">matrix</a></p></content>
      <pubDate>2007-02-05 23:29:06</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
</feed>