<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>Nikos Roussos</author>
  <title>nikos.roussos - privacy</title>
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/" />
  <updated>2016-02-01T11:00:45Z</updated>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Fighting Passive Surveillance should be our top priority</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2016/02/01/passive-surveillance/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p><img alt="massive" src="massive.jpg" /></p>
<h4><strong>Post-Snowden</strong></h4>
<p>We definitely live in a different world since Snowden leaks, but for some people nothing has changed. We always knew that certain individuals are targeted by local or international law enforcement agencies. In some cases they even have a legal way of doing this. If you work on certain fields or operate as an activist in political issues, you always assumed or knew that your communications are monitored. We may have better knowledge on the way the do it, or which things they have broken and which not yet. But essentially nothing is new about this on the post-Snowden world.</p>
<p>What Snowden leaks actually changed, what we learned from the documents, is that there is a vast ongoing process of massive passive surveillance and data collection. <strong>It doesn't matter if you are considered important. It doesn't matter if you have something to hide or not. All of your communications are monitored, stored and analyzed.</strong> This is what changed. This is what we learned.</p>
<p>Let me pause my thoughts for a moment and share a controversial story...</p>
<h4><strong>Mobile email encryption</strong></h4>
<p>Would you store your private PGP key to your mobile smartphone? Many (most?) hackers/geeks would easily answer in a negative way. Mobile phones have two major security implications that our laptops (usually) don't.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Physical security. It's more easy to lose your phone, or for someone to steal it. It's a comparatively smaller device, usually carried away in your pocket. And once you lose it, all keys stored there should be considered compromised (which is a big problem on its own, since PGP doesn't offer <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forward_secrecy">Forward Secrecy</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>More than one operating system. Even if you have taken <a href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/08/free-your-android/">all measures</a> to secure your operating system, the problem is that your phone runs also a second operating system. The "radio" OS running on your baseband chip. It's a complete proprietary black box, that you don't know what it does. You don't even know if it's isolated from your "smart" operating system.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>On a side note, mobile operating systems have a security advantage that almost all modern desktop operating systems (even most major linux distributions) lack. All applications are sandboxed. So even if you are running a malicious application (you know, like <a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2014/01/27/leaking_smartphone_apps_nsa_gchq/">Angry Birds</a>) it may do various unwanted things regarding your personal mobile usage (eg. track location) but it can't easily steal your PGP private key stored inside <a href="https://www.openkeychain.org/about/">OpenKeyChain</a>'s isolated storage. Not many desktop operating systems can protect you from a malicious application getting access to your <code>.gnupg</code> or <code>.ssh</code> folder.</p>
<p>So, although these two points are completely valid and indeed mobile smartphones are less secure, we have to realize that this is where most users read their emails. In many cases, a mobile phone is the only device people read their emails. Many people have come to cryptoparties, and after getting in touch with the complete lack of usability that comes with the standard pgp gui stack (Thunderbird + Enigmail), they ask how the can do the same things on their mobile. Most hackers would react (or even deny to help) exactly because of the reasons mentioned above. Let me clear up the dilemma a bit: Most people have two options to choose. Either use email encryption on their mobile phone or don't use encryption at all. And <strong>unfortunately most hackers fail to see that for most people the threat model is passive surveillance</strong>.</p>
<h4><strong>Threat Model</strong></h4>
<p>Not all people are trying to protect from the same things or the same type of adversaries. Not all people have the same <a href="https://ssd.eff.org/en/glossary/threat-model">Threat Model</a>.</p>
<p>I was very pleased to see Werner Koch presenting at <a href="https://events.ccc.de/congress/2015/wiki/Main_Page">32c3</a> this year about the current status of <a href="https://gnupg.org/">GnuPG</a>, where he mentioned that the focus from now on is the passive surveillance threat model. <strong>Building tools that focus on the passive surveillance threat model, means that usability and encryption by default is top priority.</strong></p>
<p>I have participated and co-organized many <a href="https://www.cryptoparty.in/athens">Cryptoparties</a>, <a href="http://wiki.fsfe.org/groups/Athens">Free Software Meetups</a>, and related crypto/privacy events/workshops. And I believe that the passive surveillance threat model should also be our focus. Yes, sometimes we need to quickly determine if a person has a different threat model (eg. journalists), but most people participating in these kind of events are not targets (at least not NSA targets). We know that they collect everything, we know that <a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2016/01/27/nsa_loves_it_when_you_use_pgp/">they love pgp</a> because it's rarely used and stands out. <strong>Let's make their job more difficult. Encrypt all things by default. Let's start  from fighting against massive passive surveillance.</strong></p>
<hr>

<p><em>Comments and reactions on <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/582762">Diaspora</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/comzeradd/status/694082702815989760">Twitter</a></em></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2016-02-01 11:01:52</published>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Multi-End Message and Object Encryption. What?</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2016/01/05/jabber-omemo/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>So, many people promoting Signal over Jabber/OTR for its usability and security features (besides all <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/497875">caveats</a>). Most of these features are offered due the <a href="https://github.com/trevp/axolotl/wiki">Axolotl Ratchet</a> protocol.</p>
<p>What if this protocol was implemented as an extension to Jabber? This would combine all best things from both worlds. Offline (encrypted) messages, multiple devices, better mobile integration but on the same time decentralized federated service. Well it’s done. Meet <a href="http://conversations.im/omemo/">OMEMO</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://conversations.im/">Conversations</a> on Android already supports it, <a href="https://chatsecure.org/blog/chatsecure-conversations-zom/">ChatSecure</a> is implementing it too and tickets are already opened on <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/16801">Pidgin</a> and <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/tor-bugs@lists.torproject.org/msg84721.html">Tor Messenger</a>. <a href="https://gajim.org/">Gajim</a> is currently the only desktop app that supports it (through <a href="https://github.com/kalkin/gajim-omemo/">a plugin</a>), but if you want to have OTR too then Gajim is not an option since <a href="https://github.com/python-otr/gajim-otr">its OTR plugin is unmaintained</a>.</p>
<p>I’ve been testing Conversations/OMEMO over the last week and it works great. So maybe in a few months we’ll have something truly secure, decentralized and usable to suggest to our friends ;) Or just suggest Conversations to the most brave of your friends.</p>
<p><img alt="omemo" src="omemo.png" /></p>
<hr />

<p><em>Comments and reactions on <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/541037">Diaspora</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/comzeradd/status/684297833453907968">Twitter</a></em></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2016-01-05 12:41:37</published>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>If you care about privacy, Signal is certainly not an option</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2015/12/05/signal-privacy/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>Whisper Systems failed big once again. They just <a href="https://whispersystems.org/blog/signal-desktop/">announced</a> their "Desktop" version of Signal, which is actually a Chrome app.</p>
<p>So just to get facts straight, this is neither a Desktop nor a Web app. And just like their Android app, you need a Google account to download it.</p>
<p>Actually this is even worse, because you also need to use Chrome to use this app. <strong>Channeling all your (meta)data through a closed source browser, built &amp; distributed by the biggest tracking ad company.</strong></p>
<p>If you care about privacy, Signal is certainly not an option.</p>
<hr />

<p><em>Comments and reactions on <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/497875">Diaspora</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/comzeradd/status/673940185692905476">Twitter</a></em></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2015-12-05 15:45:08</published>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Setup a home server with Fedora and BeagleBone Black</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/06/23/fedora-beaglebone-black/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>Over the last <a href="http://www.roussos.cc/2014/04/30/athens-free-software-monthly-meetups/">Free Software Meetup</a> we discussed about the "build your own home server" movement. This is a long and complex discussion, so most likely it will expand to future meetups. In the meantime I wanted to test BeagleBone Black (BB), as the hardware platform for such a project.</p>
<p><img src="beagle-fedora.png" alt="fedora on beaglebone black" class="txt" /> I prefer BB over Raspeberry Pi (RaPi) because, despite what many people seem to believe, RaPi <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raspberry_Pi#Driver_API">is not</a> fully Open Hardware. I also prefer armv7 hardware, since it gives me the option to use a "regular" linux distribution. I have the option for Fedora or Debian instead of Pidora or Raspbian. </p>
<p>During the meetup we talked a lot about <a href="https://arkos.io/">Arkos</a>, which supports many arm boards and seems like a great choice for administering your home server through a well designed web interface, lowering the technical knowledge threshold for setting up services like file or mail server. I'll get back to Arkos, but at this point I wanted to experiment with a "regular" distribution. So this post is about Fedora and Beaglebone Black.</p>
<p>Download the <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/en/get-fedora#arm">Fedora ARM image</a> extract it and rename it to <code>fedora-arm.raw</code> so it's easier to follow the steps bellow.</p>
<p>Flashing Fedora to BB is not that difficult. The tricky part is that Fedora comes with an "initial setup" screen, which requires an hdmi monitor and a keyboard at least on first run so you can set some basic things (like root password). I wanted to do some modifications to the Fedora image, and get through this "initial setup" screen prior to flashing it on the BB. Inspired by <a href="http://ebalaskas.gr/blog/2013/03/25/raspberry-pi-with-archlinux-under-qemu/">Ebal's post</a>, I thought Qemu as a perfect tool for this job.</p>
<pre><code>sudo yum install qemu-system-arm
</code></pre>
<p>With qemu-system-arm tool I can emulate arm and run the image on my laptop. In order to boot the image qemu needs a kernel and what better place of finding a kernel than the image itself. You can either mount the image and copy kernel and initrd out or use libguestfs (kernel and Initrd version will obviously vary on future releases).</p>
<pre><code>sudo yum install -y libguestfs-tools
virt-copy-out -a fedora-arm.raw /boot/vmlinuz-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl .
virt-copy-out -a fedora-arm.raw /boot/initramfs-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl.img .
</code></pre>
<p>Finally run it. (you may have to add your user to kvm group)</p>
<pre><code>sudo usermod -aG kvm username
newgrp kvm
qemu-system-arm -machine vexpress-a9 -m 1024 -nographic -net nic -net user \
 -append "console=ttyAMA0,115200n8 rw root=/dev/mmcblk0p3 rootwait physmap.enabled=0" \
 -kernel vmlinuz-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl \
 -initrd initramfs-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl.img \
 -sd fedora-arm.raw
</code></pre>
<p>Booting up I reached to the "initial setup" screen I mentioned before. I created a new user with administrator (aka sudo) privileges. First things I did when finally got a prompt was to disable root account:</p>
<pre><code>sudo passwd -l root
</code></pre>
<p>set a hostname</p>
<pre><code>vi /etc/sysconfig/network
</code></pre>
<p>disable Network Manger</p>
<pre><code>systemctl disable NetworkManager.service
</code></pre>
<p>setup static networking</p>
<pre><code>echo "
 HWADDR="D8:D3:85:AE:DD:4C"
 BOOTPROTO="static"
 DEVICE="eth0"
 ONBOOT="yes"
 IPADDR=192.168.1.2
 NETMASK=255.255.255.0
 BROADCAST=192.168.1.255
 NETWORK=192.168.1.0
 GATEWAY=192.168.1.1
"&gt;/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts
</code></pre>
<p>add DNS settings</p>
<pre><code>echo "
 nameserver 208.67.222.222
 nameserver 208.67.222.222
"&gt;/etc/resolv.conf
</code></pre>
<p>disable selinux (<a href="http://stopdisablingselinux.com/">sorry Dan</a>)</p>
<pre><code>setenforce 0
sed -i s/=enforcing/=disabled/ /etc/selinux/config
</code></pre>
<p>Enable ssh</p>
<pre><code>systemctl enable sshd
firewall-cmd --permanent --zone=public --add-service=ssh
</code></pre>
<p>Fedora image is around 2G. I had a 4G SDcard so I expanded it by 2G</p>
<pre><code>qemu-img resize fedora-arm.raw +2G
</code></pre>
<p>Important to remember that this will expand the image but not the root filesystem inside. Flash it to an SDcard</p>
<pre><code>dd if=fedora-arm.raw of=/dev/sdX
</code></pre>
<p>This a destructive command so make sure that sdX refers to your SDcard and not some disk. Now mount the card and resize the root filesystem, that probably would be on sdX3</p>
<pre><code>e2fsck -f /dev/sdX3
resize2fs /dev/sdX3
</code></pre>
<p>And that's all. I removed the mini sd from the adapter and inserted it on BB. All that's left is ethernet connection and power. Less than a minute later I was able to ssh to my soon-to-be home server from my laptop.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2014-06-23 13:13:52</published>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Our privacy is interdependent</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/14/our-privacy-is-interdependent/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>Last week I gave a presentation at <a href="http://commonsfest.info/">CommonsFest</a> in the spirit of my <a href="http://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/08/free-your-android/">Free Your Android</a> post, trying to educate people on simple steps they can make to have better privacy on their mobile devices.</p>
<p>A couple of days before my presentation I watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBgZyV4iltw">this great speech</a> from Jillian York and Jacob Appelbaum (please go and watch this). At some point Jacob mentions that <em>"our security is interdependent"</em>.</p>
<p>Few days later Benjamin Mako Hill came to confirm this remark, but with <a href="http://mako.cc/copyrighteous/google-has-most-of-my-email-because-it-has-all-of-yours">real evidence</a>. He analyzed his emails to find out that despite self-hosting his own mail server, 57% of his emails endup on Google's servers. I ran <a href="http://projects.mako.cc/source/?p=gmail-maildir-counter">the code</a> on my emails and I got pretty much the same percentage (and a bit higher if I include all three big providers).</p>
<p>This was how I ended my presentation (not aware of Benjamin's work at the moment):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I have made a personal choice not to host my email on Google, Microsoft or Yahoo. But if the majority of my contacts use one of these providers then most of my outgoing emails end up to their servers. It's important to understand that <strong>our privacy depends on the privacy of our social network</strong>."</p>
</blockquote>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2014-05-14 12:51:29</published>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Free Your Android</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/08/free-your-android/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>After all the recent NSA revelations, it's been even more important to use Free Software on our mobile phones. Let me express this in another way: <strong>We should be very careful about what software we use on a device that is always on and in our pocket 24h a day.</strong></p>
<p>Starting from the very basic thing that makes our smartphone operate, it seems that we don't have many options. So if you are using Iphone or Windows Phone, let me remind you that both of these companies are in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRISM_%28surveillance_program%29#The_slides">infamous NSA slides</a> for giving access to users private data.</p>
<p>So this post is about Android and my current setup of running only Free Software on my smartphone. I know what you are thinking.. that Google is also part of NSA's "special friends". Android is self-defined as an "Open Source Platform" (AOSP), and pretty much it is since it's released under a mix of Apache and GPL license (although mostly developed behind closed doors). But this isn't what you get when you buy a smartphone. Your device will certainly have preinstalled all of the Google's proprietary stuff (gmail, play, etc) and probably manufacturer and/or vendor applications. Things that you have no idea what they do, besides their "normal" functionality, because we don't have the code to look at.</p>
<h3>Operating System</h3>
<p><img src="cyanogenmod.png" alt="" class="txt" /> If you happen to be on <a href="http://redmine.replicant.us/projects/replicant/wiki/ReplicantStatus">Replicant's short list</a> of supported devices then this is the way to go. But since this applies to very few people <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org/">CyanogenMod</a> is the next best thing.</p>
<p>That's the part that is most difficult, since you have to flash your phone with the right CyanogenMod's ROM. The <a href="http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Devices">instructions on the wiki</a> are very detailed, but I know that this should look like a difficult process to non-geeks. At FSFE we run a campaign on how to <a href="https://fsfe.org/campaigns/android/liberate.en.html">free you Android</a>, so if you ever happen to find out about a "Free your Android" workshop near you location go and people will love to help you.</p>
<p>Still, if flashing your phone seems too complex skip to the next section, but at least stop using the pre-installed proprietary apps and remove any Google account you may have entered during initial phone setup (a factory reset may help).</p>
<p>CyanogenMod is not perfect. It contains <a href="https://github.com/CyanogenMod/android_device_semc_iyokan/blob/gingerbread/extract-files.sh">scripts that extract</a> proprietary code necessary for some phone components (eg. camera) to work. The good thing is that these parts are firmware, thus non-executable code. You may also need to tweak it a bit:</p>
<ul>
<li>Remove Google analytics from CyanogenMod by flashing <a href="https://github.com/mar-v-in/freecyngn">freecygn</a>.</li>
<li>Stop CyanogenMod from reporting tethering usage to your provider, by <a href="https://pmf.silvrback.com/fixing-tethering-on-android-kitkat">changing the "tether dun required" setting</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://blog.varunkumar.me/2010/09/how-to-change-dns-server-on-android.html">Change DNS settings</a> so that CyanogenMod stops using Google's DNS servers, that has a permanent log policy.</li>
<li>Choose to fully encrypt your device with a pin (Settings -&gt; Security -&gt; Encrypt phone).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Apps</h3>
<p><img src="fdroid.png" alt="" class="txt" width="130" /> Since we got rid Google apps, one way or another, we need a way to install software to our phone. Free Software. <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-droid</a> comes to the rescue, an app for accessing software repositories for android and that comes preconfigured with its own repository containing only Free Software apps. Install it and then head over to <a href="https://guardianproject.info/2012/03/15/our-new-f-droid-app-repository/">Guardian project</a> to add its repository to F-droid. I won't provide links for the apps below, since you can easily install them through F-droid.
<br><br></p>
<h4>Contacts / Calendar</h4>
<p><em>DavDroid</em> is an app for synchronizing Contacts and Calendar. It supports both CalDAV and CardDAV, so you will be able to set it with your provider or self hosted service.</p>
<p><img src="davdroid.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Email</h4>
<p><em>K9</em> is the ultimate email client for Android. It has all the features you would expect from a mail client. You can combine it with <em>AGP</em> or <em>OpenKeychain</em> for PGP (I prefer the second, since AGP doesn't support subkeys yet).</p>
<p><img src="k9.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="apg.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="keychain.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Browser</h4>
<p>Well... <em>Firefox</em>. You can add some of the usual privacy Add-ons. <em>Orweb</em> is a browser preconfigured for anonymous access to the web through the Tor network.</p>
<p><img src="firefox.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="orweb.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Files / Photos</h4>
<p>I have an <a href="http://owncloud.org/">Owncloud</a> instance and although I use it mostly for Contacts/Calendar (I prefer <a href="http://sparkleshare.org/">Sparkleshare</a> for files) I find it really handy that my photos can be synced automatically with OwnCloud and accessed directly from my laptop. <a href="http://seafile.com/">Seafile</a> also seems like a great choice, but haven't tested it yet.</p>
<p><img src="owncloud.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="seafile.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Maps</h4>
<p><em>OsmAnd</em> is the best maps android application (yes better than Google maps), mostly due to its great offline feature. Map data come straight from the work of <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a> contributors. I always install <em>OSMTracker</em> to my phone to be able to contribute myself and GPSLogger to log <a href="http://ridewithgps.com/users/80721">my bike rides</a>.</p>
<p><img src="osmand.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="osmtracker.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="gpslogger.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>News</h4>
<p><em>TTRSS-Reader</em> is the android version of the well known Free Software RSS reader <a href="http://tt-rss.org/">TinyTinyRSS</a>. It will play along with both self hosted and 3rd party instances. <em>Poche</em> helps saving articles to "Read them later" on a <a href="https://www.wallabag.org/">Wallabag</a> instance.</p>
<p><img src="ttrssreader.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="wallabag.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Chat</h4>
<p>XMPP (Jabber) is the obvious choice for instance messaging. <em>ChatSecure</em> and <em>Xabber</em> are the best android apps for that job. Both support OTR for encrypted communication, but ChatSecure is better on this field since it can be combined with <a href="https://guardianproject.info/apps/keysync/">KeySync</a> and sync your OTR keys with the ones you keep on your desktop client.</p>
<p><img src="chatsecure.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="xabber.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Documents / Ebooks</h4>
<p>I prefer reading on my Kobo, but in case you want an epub reader <em>FBReader</em> will be a good choice. <em>Document Viewer</em> opens pdf documents (plays well with mail attachments).</p>
<p><img src="fbreader.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="documentviewer.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Social / Microblogging</h4>
<p>I use <em>Twidere</em> for Twitter. Great app. Supports StatusNet too. There is also a <em>Diaspora Webclient</em> app, that seems to just wrap Diaspora's mobile web interface.</p>
<p><img src="twidere.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="diaspora.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>VoIP</h4>
<p>Guardian project has setup an SIP provider (<a href="https://ostel.co/">Ostel.co</a>) that just works, encrypting calls by default (aka <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZRTP">ZRTP</a>). They suggest <em>CSipSimple</em> for using this android, but I've tried <em>Lumicall</em> and works great.</p>
<p><img src="lumicall.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="ostel.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<p><img src="fya.png" alt="" width="120" /> </p>
<p>All the software I mention here is stuff I use. I'm sure that in some cases you may find alternatives that better suit your needs. So dig deeper to F-droid for more apps and surf through <a href="https://fsfe.org/campaigns/android/liberate.en.html">FSFE's website</a>.</p>
<p>I currently have an android smartphone that runs 100% Free Software applications. I can't think of missing any functionality so far and I certainly feel more secure ;)</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2014-05-08 11:22:03</published>
    </entry>
  
</feed>