<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>Nikos Roussos</author>
  <title>nikos.roussos &bull; privacy</title>
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/" />
  
    <entry>
      <title>Multi-End Message and Object Encryption. What?</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2016/01/05/jabber-omemo/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>So, many people promoting Signal over Jabber/OTR for its usability and security features (besides all <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/497875">caveats</a>). Most of these features are offered due the <a href="https://github.com/trevp/axolotl/wiki">Axolotl Ratchet</a> protocol.</p>
<p>What if this protocol was implemented as an extension to Jabber? This would combine all best things from both worlds. Offline (encrypted) messages, multiple devices, better mobile integration but on the same time decentralized federated service. Well it’s done. Meet <a href="http://conversations.im/omemo/">OMEMO</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://conversations.im/">Conversations</a> on Android already supports it, <a href="https://chatsecure.org/blog/chatsecure-conversations-zom/">ChatSecure</a> is implementing it too and tickets are already opened on <a href="https://developer.pidgin.im/ticket/16801">Pidgin</a> and <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/tor-bugs@lists.torproject.org/msg84721.html">Tor Messenger</a>. <a href="https://gajim.org/">Gajim</a> is currently the only desktop app that supports it (through <a href="https://github.com/kalkin/gajim-omemo/">a plugin</a>), but if you want to have OTR too then Gajim is not an option since <a href="https://github.com/python-otr/gajim-otr">its OTR plugin is unmaintained</a>.</p>
<p>I’ve been testing Conversations/OMEMO over the last week and it works great. So maybe in a few months we’ll have something truly secure, decentralized and usable to suggest to our friends ;) Or just suggest Conversations to the most brave of your friends.</p>
<p><img alt="omemo" src="omemo.png" /></p>
<hr />

<p><em>Comments and reactions on <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/541037">Diaspora</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/comzeradd/status/684297833453907968">Twitter</a></em></p></content>
      <pubDate>2016-01-05 12:41:37</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>If you care about privacy, Signal is certainly not an option</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2015/12/05/signal-privacy/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>Whisper Systems failed big once again. They just <a href="https://whispersystems.org/blog/signal-desktop/">announced</a> their "Desktop" version of Signal, which is actually a Chrome app.</p>
<p>So just to get facts straight, this is neither a Desktop nor a Web app. And just like their Android app, you need a Google account to download it.</p>
<p>Actually this is even worse, because you also need to use Chrome to use this app. <strong>Channeling all your (meta)data through a closed source browser, built &amp; distributed by the biggest tracking ad company.</strong></p>
<p>If you care about privacy, Signal is certainly not an option.</p>
<hr />

<p><em>Comments and reactions on <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/497875">Diaspora</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/comzeradd/status/673940185692905476">Twitter</a></em></p></content>
      <pubDate>2015-12-05 15:45:08</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Setup a home server with Fedora and BeagleBone Black</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/06/23/fedora-beaglebone-black/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>Over the last <a href="http://www.roussos.cc/2014/04/30/athens-free-software-monthly-meetups/">Free Software Meetup</a> we discussed about the "build your own home server" movement. This is a long and complex discussion, so most likely it will expand to future meetups. In the meantime I wanted to test BeagleBone Black (BB), as the hardware platform for such a project.</p>
<p><img src="beagle-fedora.png" alt="fedora on beaglebone black" class="txt" /> I prefer BB over Raspeberry Pi (RaPi) because, despite what many people seem to believe, RaPi <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raspberry_Pi#Driver_API">is not</a> fully Open Hardware. I also prefer armv7 hardware, since it gives me the option to use a "regular" linux distribution. I have the option for Fedora or Debian instead of Pidora or Raspbian. </p>
<p>During the meetup we talked a lot about <a href="https://arkos.io/">Arkos</a>, which supports many arm boards and seems like a great choice for administering your home server through a well designed web interface, lowering the technical knowledge threshold for setting up services like file or mail server. I'll get back to Arkos, but at this point I wanted to experiment with a "regular" distribution. So this post is about Fedora and Beaglebone Black.</p>
<p>Download the <a href="http://fedoraproject.org/en/get-fedora#arm">Fedora ARM image</a> extract it and rename it to <code>fedora-arm.raw</code> so it's easier to follow the steps bellow.</p>
<p>Flashing Fedora to BB is not that difficult. The tricky part is that Fedora comes with an "initial setup" screen, which requires an hdmi monitor and a keyboard at least on first run so you can set some basic things (like root password). I wanted to do some modifications to the Fedora image, and get through this "initial setup" screen prior to flashing it on the BB. Inspired by <a href="http://ebalaskas.gr/blog/2013/03/25/raspberry-pi-with-archlinux-under-qemu/">Ebal's post</a>, I thought Qemu as a perfect tool for this job.</p>
<pre><code>sudo yum install qemu-system-arm
</code></pre>
<p>With qemu-system-arm tool I can emulate arm and run the image on my laptop. In order to boot the image qemu needs a kernel and what better place of finding a kernel than the image itself. You can either mount the image and copy kernel and initrd out or use libguestfs (kernel and Initrd version will obviously vary on future releases).</p>
<pre><code>sudo yum install -y libguestfs-tools
virt-copy-out -a fedora-arm.raw /boot/vmlinuz-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl .
virt-copy-out -a fedora-arm.raw /boot/initramfs-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl.img .
</code></pre>
<p>Finally run it. (you may have to add your user to kvm group)</p>
<pre><code>sudo usermod -aG kvm username
newgrp kvm
qemu-system-arm -machine vexpress-a9 -m 1024 -nographic -net nic -net user \
 -append "console=ttyAMA0,115200n8 rw root=/dev/mmcblk0p3 rootwait physmap.enabled=0" \
 -kernel vmlinuz-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl \
 -initrd initramfs-3.11.10-301.fc20.armv7hl.img \
 -sd fedora-arm.raw
</code></pre>
<p>Booting up I reached to the "initial setup" screen I mentioned before. I created a new user with administrator (aka sudo) privileges. First things I did when finally got a prompt was to disable root account:</p>
<pre><code>sudo passwd -l root
</code></pre>
<p>set a hostname</p>
<pre><code>vi /etc/sysconfig/network
</code></pre>
<p>disable Network Manger</p>
<pre><code>systemctl disable NetworkManager.service
</code></pre>
<p>setup static networking</p>
<pre><code>echo "
 HWADDR="D8:D3:85:AE:DD:4C"
 BOOTPROTO="static"
 DEVICE="eth0"
 ONBOOT="yes"
 IPADDR=192.168.1.2
 NETMASK=255.255.255.0
 BROADCAST=192.168.1.255
 NETWORK=192.168.1.0
 GATEWAY=192.168.1.1
"&gt;/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts
</code></pre>
<p>add DNS settings</p>
<pre><code>echo "
 nameserver 208.67.222.222
 nameserver 208.67.222.222
"&gt;/etc/resolv.conf
</code></pre>
<p>disable selinux (<a href="http://stopdisablingselinux.com/">sorry Dan</a>)</p>
<pre><code>setenforce 0
sed -i s/=enforcing/=disabled/ /etc/selinux/config
</code></pre>
<p>Enable ssh</p>
<pre><code>systemctl enable sshd
firewall-cmd --permanent --zone=public --add-service=ssh
</code></pre>
<p>Fedora image is around 2G. I had a 4G SDcard so I expanded it by 2G</p>
<pre><code>qemu-img resize fedora-arm.raw +2G
</code></pre>
<p>Important to remember that this will expand the image but not the root filesystem inside. Flash it to an SDcard</p>
<pre><code>dd if=fedora-arm.raw of=/dev/sdX
</code></pre>
<p>This a destructive command so make sure that sdX refers to your SDcard and not some disk. Now mount the card and resize the root filesystem, that probably would be on sdX3</p>
<pre><code>e2fsck -f /dev/sdX3
resize2fs /dev/sdX3
</code></pre>
<p>And that's all. I removed the mini sd from the adapter and inserted it on BB. All that's left is ethernet connection and power. Less than a minute later I was able to ssh to my soon-to-be home server from my laptop.</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-06-23 13:13:52</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Our privacy is interdependent</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/14/our-privacy-is-interdependent/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>Last week I gave a presentation at <a href="http://commonsfest.info/">CommonsFest</a> in the spirit of my <a href="http://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/08/free-your-android/">Free Your Android</a> post, trying to educate people on simple steps they can make to have better privacy on their mobile devices.</p>
<p>A couple of days before my presentation I watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BBgZyV4iltw">this great speech</a> from Jillian York and Jacob Appelbaum (please go and watch this). At some point Jacob mentions that <em>"our security is interdependent"</em>.</p>
<p>Few days later Benjamin Mako Hill came to confirm this remark, but with <a href="http://mako.cc/copyrighteous/google-has-most-of-my-email-because-it-has-all-of-yours">real evidence</a>. He analyzed his emails to find out that despite self-hosting his own mail server, 57% of his emails endup on Google's servers. I ran <a href="http://projects.mako.cc/source/?p=gmail-maildir-counter">the code</a> on my emails and I got pretty much the same percentage (and a bit higher if I include all three big providers).</p>
<p>This was how I ended my presentation (not aware of Benjamin's work at the moment):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"I have made a personal choice not to host my email on Google, Microsoft or Yahoo. But if the majority of my contacts use one of these providers then most of my outgoing emails end up to their servers. It's important to understand that <strong>our privacy depends on the privacy of our social network</strong>."</p>
</blockquote></content>
      <pubDate>2014-05-14 12:51:29</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Free Your Android</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/05/08/free-your-android/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>After all the recent NSA revelations, it's been even more important to use Free Software on our mobile phones. Let me express this in another way: <strong>We should be very careful about what software we use on a device that is always on and in our pocket 24h a day.</strong></p>
<p>Starting from the very basic thing that makes our smartphone operate, it seems that we don't have many options. So if you are using Iphone or Windows Phone, let me remind you that both of these companies are in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PRISM_%28surveillance_program%29#The_slides">infamous NSA slides</a> for giving access to users private data.</p>
<p>So this post is about Android and my current setup of running only Free Software on my smartphone. I know what you are thinking.. that Google is also part of NSA's "special friends". Android is self-defined as an "Open Source Platform" (AOSP), and pretty much it is since it's released under a mix of Apache and GPL license (although mostly developed behind closed doors). But this isn't what you get when you buy a smartphone. Your device will certainly have preinstalled all of the Google's proprietary stuff (gmail, play, etc) and probably manufacturer and/or vendor applications. Things that you have no idea what they do, besides their "normal" functionality, because we don't have the code to look at.</p>
<h3>Operating System</h3>
<p><img src="cyanogenmod.png" alt="" class="txt" /> If you happen to be on <a href="http://redmine.replicant.us/projects/replicant/wiki/ReplicantStatus">Replicant's short list</a> of supported devices then this is the way to go. But since this applies to very few people <a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org/">CyanogenMod</a> is the next best thing.</p>
<p>That's the part that is most difficult, since you have to flash your phone with the right CyanogenMod's ROM. The <a href="http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Devices">instructions on the wiki</a> are very detailed, but I know that this should look like a difficult process to non-geeks. At FSFE we run a campaign on how to <a href="https://fsfe.org/campaigns/android/liberate.en.html">free you Android</a>, so if you ever happen to find out about a "Free your Android" workshop near you location go and people will love to help you.</p>
<p>Still, if flashing your phone seems too complex skip to the next section, but at least stop using the pre-installed proprietary apps and remove any Google account you may have entered during initial phone setup (a factory reset may help).</p>
<p>CyanogenMod is not perfect. It contains <a href="https://github.com/CyanogenMod/android_device_semc_iyokan/blob/gingerbread/extract-files.sh">scripts that extract</a> proprietary code necessary for some phone components (eg. camera) to work. The good thing is that these parts are firmware, thus non-executable code. You may also need to tweak it a bit:</p>
<ul>
<li>Remove Google analytics from CyanogenMod by flashing <a href="https://github.com/mar-v-in/freecyngn">freecygn</a>.</li>
<li>Stop CyanogenMod from reporting tethering usage to your provider, by <a href="https://pmf.silvrback.com/fixing-tethering-on-android-kitkat">changing the "tether dun required" setting</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://blog.varunkumar.me/2010/09/how-to-change-dns-server-on-android.html">Change DNS settings</a> so that CyanogenMod stops using Google's DNS servers, that has a permanent log policy.</li>
<li>Choose to fully encrypt your device with a pin (Settings -&gt; Security -&gt; Encrypt phone).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Apps</h3>
<p><img src="fdroid.png" alt="" class="txt" width="130" /> Since we got rid Google apps, one way or another, we need a way to install software to our phone. Free Software. <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-droid</a> comes to the rescue, an app for accessing software repositories for android and that comes preconfigured with its own repository containing only Free Software apps. Install it and then head over to <a href="https://guardianproject.info/2012/03/15/our-new-f-droid-app-repository/">Guardian project</a> to add its repository to F-droid. I won't provide links for the apps below, since you can easily install them through F-droid.
<br><br></p>
<h4>Contacts / Calendar</h4>
<p><em>DavDroid</em> is an app for synchronizing Contacts and Calendar. It supports both CalDAV and CardDAV, so you will be able to set it with your provider or self hosted service.</p>
<p><img src="davdroid.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Email</h4>
<p><em>K9</em> is the ultimate email client for Android. It has all the features you would expect from a mail client. You can combine it with <em>AGP</em> or <em>OpenKeychain</em> for PGP (I prefer the second, since AGP doesn't support subkeys yet).</p>
<p><img src="k9.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="apg.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="keychain.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Browser</h4>
<p>Well... <em>Firefox</em>. You can add some of the usual privacy Add-ons. <em>Orweb</em> is a browser preconfigured for anonymous access to the web through the Tor network.</p>
<p><img src="firefox.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="orweb.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Files / Photos</h4>
<p>I have an <a href="http://owncloud.org/">Owncloud</a> instance and although I use it mostly for Contacts/Calendar (I prefer <a href="http://sparkleshare.org/">Sparkleshare</a> for files) I find it really handy that my photos can be synced automatically with OwnCloud and accessed directly from my laptop. <a href="http://seafile.com/">Seafile</a> also seems like a great choice, but haven't tested it yet.</p>
<p><img src="owncloud.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="seafile.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Maps</h4>
<p><em>OsmAnd</em> is the best maps android application (yes better than Google maps), mostly due to its great offline feature. Map data come straight from the work of <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a> contributors. I always install <em>OSMTracker</em> to my phone to be able to contribute myself and GPSLogger to log <a href="http://ridewithgps.com/users/80721">my bike rides</a>.</p>
<p><img src="osmand.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="osmtracker.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="gpslogger.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>News</h4>
<p><em>TTRSS-Reader</em> is the android version of the well known Free Software RSS reader <a href="http://tt-rss.org/">TinyTinyRSS</a>. It will play along with both self hosted and 3rd party instances. <em>Poche</em> helps saving articles to "Read them later" on a <a href="https://www.wallabag.org/">Wallabag</a> instance.</p>
<p><img src="ttrssreader.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="wallabag.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Chat</h4>
<p>XMPP (Jabber) is the obvious choice for instance messaging. <em>ChatSecure</em> and <em>Xabber</em> are the best android apps for that job. Both support OTR for encrypted communication, but ChatSecure is better on this field since it can be combined with <a href="https://guardianproject.info/apps/keysync/">KeySync</a> and sync your OTR keys with the ones you keep on your desktop client.</p>
<p><img src="chatsecure.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="xabber.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Documents / Ebooks</h4>
<p>I prefer reading on my Kobo, but in case you want an epub reader <em>FBReader</em> will be a good choice. <em>Document Viewer</em> opens pdf documents (plays well with mail attachments).</p>
<p><img src="fbreader.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="documentviewer.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>Social / Microblogging</h4>
<p>I use <em>Twidere</em> for Twitter. Great app. Supports StatusNet too. There is also a <em>Diaspora Webclient</em> app, that seems to just wrap Diaspora's mobile web interface.</p>
<p><img src="twidere.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="diaspora.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<h4>VoIP</h4>
<p>Guardian project has setup an SIP provider (<a href="https://ostel.co/">Ostel.co</a>) that just works, encrypting calls by default (aka <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZRTP">ZRTP</a>). They suggest <em>CSipSimple</em> for using this android, but I've tried <em>Lumicall</em> and works great.</p>
<p><img src="lumicall.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /> <img src="ostel.png" alt="" class="txt" width="32" /><br><br></p>
<p><img src="fya.png" alt="" width="120" /> </p>
<p>All the software I mention here is stuff I use. I'm sure that in some cases you may find alternatives that better suit your needs. So dig deeper to F-droid for more apps and surf through <a href="https://fsfe.org/campaigns/android/liberate.en.html">FSFE's website</a>.</p>
<p>I currently have an android smartphone that runs 100% Free Software applications. I can't think of missing any functionality so far and I certainly feel more secure ;)</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-05-08 11:22:03</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Making things distributed is hard</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/03/12/making-things-distributed-is-hard/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>One of the most interesting rants I have ever read, by Maciej Cegłowski.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Technology concentrates power.</p>
<p>In the 90's, it looked like the Internet might be an exception, that it could be a decentralizing, democratizing force. No one controlled it, no one designed it, it was just kind of assembling itself in an appealing, anarchic way. The companies that first tried to centralize the Internet, like AOL and Microsoft, failed risibly. And open source looked ready to slay any dragon.</p>
<p>But those days are gone. We've centralized the bejesus out of the Internet now. There's <a href="http://www.lycos.com/">one search engine</a> (plus the one no one uses), <a href="http://myspace.com/">one social network</a> (plus the one no one uses), one Twitter. We use one ad network, one analytics suite. Anywhere you look online, one or two giant American companies utterly dominate the field.</p>
<p>And there's the cloud. What a brilliant name! The cloud is the future of online computing, a friendly, fluffy abstraction that we will all ascend into, swaddled in light. But really the cloud is just a large mess of servers somewhere, the property of one American company (plus the clouds no one uses).</p>
<p>Orwell imagined a world with a <a href="http://www.theorwellreader.com/excerpt.shtml">telescreen in every room</a>, always on, always connected, always monitored. An <a href="http://au.ign.com/wikis/xbox-one/Xbox_One_Kinect">Xbox One</a> vision of dystopia.</p>
<p>But we've done him one better. Nearly everyone here carries in their pocket a tracking device that knows where you are, who you talk to, what you look at, all these intimate details of your life, and sedulously reports them to private servers where the data is stored in perpetuity.</p>
<p>I know I sound like a conspiracy nut framing it like this. I'm not saying we live in an Orwellian nightmare. I love New Zealand! But we have the technology.</p>
<p>When I was in grade school, they used to scare us with something called the permanent record. If you threw a spitball at your friend, it would go in your permanent record, and prevent you getting a good job, or marrying well, until eventually you'd die young and friendless and be buried outside the churchyard wall.</p>
<p>What a relief when we found out that the permanent record was a fiction. Except now we've gone and implemented the damned thing. Each of us leaves an indelible, comet-like trail across the Internet that cannot be erased and that we're not even allowed to see.</p>
<p>The things we really care about seem to disappear from the Internet immediately, but post a stupid YouTube comment (now linked to your real identity) and it will live forever.</p>
<p>And we have to track all this stuff, because the economic basis of today's web is advertising, or the promise of future advertising. The only way we can convince investors to keep the money flowing is by keeping the most detailed records possible, tied to people's real identities. Apart from a few corners of anonymity, which not by accident are the <a href="http://chrishateswriting.com/post/76431353368/the-anonymity-i-know">most culturally vibrant parts</a> of the Internet, everything is tracked and has to be tracked or the edifice collapses.</p>
<p>What upsets me isn't that we created this centralized version of the Internet based on permanent surveillance.</p>
<p>What upsets me, what really gets my goat, is that we did it because it was the easiest thing to do. There was no design, forethought, or analysis involved. No one said "hey, this sounds like a great world to live in, let's make it". It happened because we couldn't be bothered.</p>
<p>Making things ephemeral is hard.</p>
<p>Making things distributed is hard.</p>
<p>Making things anonymous is hard.</p>
<p>Coming up with a sane business model is really hard—I get tired just thinking about it.</p>
<p>So let's take people's data, throw it on a server, link it to their Facebook profiles, keep it forever, and if we can't raise another round of venture funding we'll just slap Google ads on the thing.</p>
<p>"High five, Chad!"</p>
<p>"High five, bro!"</p>
<p>That is the design process that went into building the Internet of 2014.</p>
<p>And of course now we are shocked—shocked!—when, for example, the Ukrainian government uses cell tower data to send scary text messages to protesters in Kiev, in order to try to keep them off the streets. Bad people are using the global surveillance system we built to do something mean! Holy crap! Who could have imagined this?</p>
<p>Or when we learn that the American government is reading the email that you send unencrypted to the ad-supported mail service in another country where it gets archived forever. Inconceivable!</p>
<p>I'm not saying these abuses aren't serious. But they're the opposite of surprising. People will always abuse power. That's not a new insight. There are cuneiform tablets complaining about it. Yet here we are in 2014, startled because unscrupulous people have started to use the powerful tools we created for them.</p>
<p>We put so much care into making the Internet resilient from technical failures, but make no effort to make it resilient to political failure. We treat freedom and the rule of law like inexhaustible natural resources, rather than the fragile and precious treasures that they are.</p>
<p>And now, of course, it's time to make the Internet of Things, where we will connect everything to everything else, and build cool apps on top, and nothing can possibly go wrong. </p>
<p>Not long ago before I flew here, Google announced it was acquiring Nest, a luxury thermostat maker. I never thought I would use those two words together. Nest has sensors that detect who is in a room and when, so naturally there was concern that Google would now learn all this extra information about you, and know how hot your house is.</p>
<p>Google quickly deployed the Nest CEO, who promised that there would be safeguards and a privacy policy, and all kinds limits to make sure everything stayed kosher. And I have no reason to disbelieve the guy.</p>
<p>But I shouldn't need his word, or Google's corporate motto, or Magna Carta, or the <a href="http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/politics/treaty/the-treaty-in-brief">Treaty of Waitangi</a> to protect me from my thermostat. My old thermostat wasn't that scary! It was too dumb to snitch. And no one could hear it scream.</p>
<p>This new thermostat, on the other hand, has lawyers, PR people, a privacy policy, it's off writing blog posts somewhere, possibly eating my leftover pizza. It more like a sketchy roommate than a thermostat.</p>
<p>Let me make it clear what I'm worried about here. I'm not afraid of my appliances. I'm not afraid that Google is going to send me to the Googlag to mine bitcoins.</p>
<p>Nor am I afraid of a Greater New Zealand, grown drunk with electronic surveillance, aggressively expanding to control the Pacific Rim. That might be a nice change! If it happens, I will be waiting on the docks of San Francisco, bearing a basket of avocados, ready to welcome our Kiwi overlords.</p>
<p>What I'm afraid of is the society we already live in. Where people like you and me, if we stay inside the lines, can enjoy lives of comfort and relative ease, but God help anyone who is declared out of bounds. Those people will feel the full might of the high-tech modern state.</p>
<p>Consider your neighbors across the Tasman, stewards of an empty continent, who have <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Solution">set up internment camps in the remotest parts of the Pacific</a> for fear that a few thousand indigent people might come in on boats, take low-wage jobs, and thereby destroy their society.</p>
<p>Or the country I live in, where we have a bipartisan consensus that the only way to preserve our freedom is to fly remote controlled planes that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drone_attacks_in_Pakistan#Civilian_casualties">occasionally drop bombs on children</a>. It's <a href="http://classiclit.about.com/od/brotherskaramazov/a/aa_brothersqut.htm">straight out of Dostoevski</a>.</p>
<p>Except Dostoevski needed a doorstop of a book to grapple with the question: “Is it ever acceptable for innocents to suffer for the greater good?” And the Americans, a more practical people, have answered that in two words: “Of course!”</p>
<p>Erika Hall in <a href="http://www.webstock.org.nz/14/programme/presentations/#hall">her talk yesterday</a> wondered what Mao or Stalin could have done with the resources of the modern Internet. It's a good question. If you look at the history of the KGB or Stasi, they consumed enormous resources just maintaining and cross-referencing their mountains of paperwork. There's a throwaway line in Huxley's Brave New World where he mentions "800 cubic meters of card catalogs" in the eugenic baby factory. Imagine what Stalin could have done with a decent MySQL server.</p>
<p>We haven't seen yet what a truly bad government is capable of doing with modern information technology. What the good ones get up to is terrifying enough.</p>
<p>I'm not saying we can't have the fun next-generation Internet, where everyone wears stupid goggles and has profound conversations with their refrigerator. I'm just saying we can't slap it together like we've been doing so far and expect everything to work itself out.</p>
<p>The good news is, it's a design problem! You're all designers here - we can make it fun! We can build an Internet that's distributed, resilient, irritating to governments everywhere, and free in the best sense of the word, like we dreamed of in the 90's. But it will take effort and determination. It will mean scrapping permanent mass surveillance as a business model, which is going to hurt. It will mean pushing laws through a sclerotic legal system. There will have to be some nagging.</p>
<p>But if we don't design this Internet, if we just continue to build it out, then eventually it will attract some remarkable, visionary people. And we're not going to like them, and it's not going to matter.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can read the <a href="https://static.pinboard.in/webstock_2014.htm">full transcript</a> of the presentation (which actually is about the life of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A9on_Theremin">Lev Sergeyevich Termen</a>).</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-03-12 14:41:16</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>A short story about mass surveillance</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/02/13/a-story-about-mass-surveillance/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>So imagine you have a camera in your house. In your living room. A surveillance camera, like those you see in a metro station. In fact not just in your house (because hey, after all you are not that important), but in everyone's house. Image there is a surveillance camera on every living room. Creepy right? Would you just let it there staring and watching at you? Every movement you make in your own house? Well this is what is going on right now. No seriously. This is what is happening; but in the digital world. You see a physical camera is so easy to spot and get you frustrated. But on the digital world, which is as real as the physical one, the surveillance mechanisms are not so easy to spot.</p>
<p>So I'm having this camera in my living room watching every move I make. and the other day Maria, a friend of mine, comes for a cup of coffee in my house. She comes from another country, with different surveillance methods and she's surprised to see the camera. <em>"You know you have a camera in your house? Over there in that corner of the ceiling."</em>. There are plenty of ways I could react to this remark. The obvious one would be to look her finger and not where it's pointing, pretending there is nothing there. Or I could start yelling at her <em>"Oh, come on. I know you people, all you do is scare people off. There is no camera! Don't try to terrorize us"</em>. Another approach would be that I actually get scared, censor myself and act as "normal" as I can. You know just sit there quietly and open my tv. Because that's what normal people do, right? I don't want to look suspicious and draw any attention on me from whoever is behind this camera. Until of course I really believe this and become that man who watches tv all day doing nothing out of the ordinary. Or... I could just thank Maria for stating the obvious and start thinking about what we can do about it.</p>
<p>A couple of hours later George, another friend, joins our company. He is more into technology than the average people. Actually a lot more. You know, these people that you can watch for hours talking only with acronyms and unknown words. So the discussion comes up again at this disturbing surveillance thing and he points out that there is a way to protect myself. A technical way to hide and obfuscate my movements inside my house, so they can't see what I'm doing (or at least make their job a lot harder). Well again there are various ways I could react to this. I could deny taking any measures to protect myself because that would make me look suspicious. I'm not that important. Let them focus on those who have something to hide. Or I could claim that this is a political problem and the only solution would be a political one. No technical measures can help us, so I refuse even to bother about them. Or... I could just thank George for having the patience to educate me about these things, and yes I would acknowledge the fact that this is a political problem and in the long term the solution should be political. But in the meantime I'm going to make their job a hell of a lot difficult. I'm going to help everyone look suspicious.</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-02-13 11:50:16</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
</feed>