<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>Nikos Roussos</author>
  <title>nikos.roussos &bull; mozilla</title>
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/" />
  
    <entry>
      <title>Making things distributed is hard</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/03/12/making-things-distributed-is-hard/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>One of the most interesting rants I have ever read, by Maciej Cegłowski.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Technology concentrates power.</p>
<p>In the 90's, it looked like the Internet might be an exception, that it could be a decentralizing, democratizing force. No one controlled it, no one designed it, it was just kind of assembling itself in an appealing, anarchic way. The companies that first tried to centralize the Internet, like AOL and Microsoft, failed risibly. And open source looked ready to slay any dragon.</p>
<p>But those days are gone. We've centralized the bejesus out of the Internet now. There's <a href="http://www.lycos.com/">one search engine</a> (plus the one no one uses), <a href="http://myspace.com/">one social network</a> (plus the one no one uses), one Twitter. We use one ad network, one analytics suite. Anywhere you look online, one or two giant American companies utterly dominate the field.</p>
<p>And there's the cloud. What a brilliant name! The cloud is the future of online computing, a friendly, fluffy abstraction that we will all ascend into, swaddled in light. But really the cloud is just a large mess of servers somewhere, the property of one American company (plus the clouds no one uses).</p>
<p>Orwell imagined a world with a <a href="http://www.theorwellreader.com/excerpt.shtml">telescreen in every room</a>, always on, always connected, always monitored. An <a href="http://au.ign.com/wikis/xbox-one/Xbox_One_Kinect">Xbox One</a> vision of dystopia.</p>
<p>But we've done him one better. Nearly everyone here carries in their pocket a tracking device that knows where you are, who you talk to, what you look at, all these intimate details of your life, and sedulously reports them to private servers where the data is stored in perpetuity.</p>
<p>I know I sound like a conspiracy nut framing it like this. I'm not saying we live in an Orwellian nightmare. I love New Zealand! But we have the technology.</p>
<p>When I was in grade school, they used to scare us with something called the permanent record. If you threw a spitball at your friend, it would go in your permanent record, and prevent you getting a good job, or marrying well, until eventually you'd die young and friendless and be buried outside the churchyard wall.</p>
<p>What a relief when we found out that the permanent record was a fiction. Except now we've gone and implemented the damned thing. Each of us leaves an indelible, comet-like trail across the Internet that cannot be erased and that we're not even allowed to see.</p>
<p>The things we really care about seem to disappear from the Internet immediately, but post a stupid YouTube comment (now linked to your real identity) and it will live forever.</p>
<p>And we have to track all this stuff, because the economic basis of today's web is advertising, or the promise of future advertising. The only way we can convince investors to keep the money flowing is by keeping the most detailed records possible, tied to people's real identities. Apart from a few corners of anonymity, which not by accident are the <a href="http://chrishateswriting.com/post/76431353368/the-anonymity-i-know">most culturally vibrant parts</a> of the Internet, everything is tracked and has to be tracked or the edifice collapses.</p>
<p>What upsets me isn't that we created this centralized version of the Internet based on permanent surveillance.</p>
<p>What upsets me, what really gets my goat, is that we did it because it was the easiest thing to do. There was no design, forethought, or analysis involved. No one said "hey, this sounds like a great world to live in, let's make it". It happened because we couldn't be bothered.</p>
<p>Making things ephemeral is hard.</p>
<p>Making things distributed is hard.</p>
<p>Making things anonymous is hard.</p>
<p>Coming up with a sane business model is really hard—I get tired just thinking about it.</p>
<p>So let's take people's data, throw it on a server, link it to their Facebook profiles, keep it forever, and if we can't raise another round of venture funding we'll just slap Google ads on the thing.</p>
<p>"High five, Chad!"</p>
<p>"High five, bro!"</p>
<p>That is the design process that went into building the Internet of 2014.</p>
<p>And of course now we are shocked—shocked!—when, for example, the Ukrainian government uses cell tower data to send scary text messages to protesters in Kiev, in order to try to keep them off the streets. Bad people are using the global surveillance system we built to do something mean! Holy crap! Who could have imagined this?</p>
<p>Or when we learn that the American government is reading the email that you send unencrypted to the ad-supported mail service in another country where it gets archived forever. Inconceivable!</p>
<p>I'm not saying these abuses aren't serious. But they're the opposite of surprising. People will always abuse power. That's not a new insight. There are cuneiform tablets complaining about it. Yet here we are in 2014, startled because unscrupulous people have started to use the powerful tools we created for them.</p>
<p>We put so much care into making the Internet resilient from technical failures, but make no effort to make it resilient to political failure. We treat freedom and the rule of law like inexhaustible natural resources, rather than the fragile and precious treasures that they are.</p>
<p>And now, of course, it's time to make the Internet of Things, where we will connect everything to everything else, and build cool apps on top, and nothing can possibly go wrong. </p>
<p>Not long ago before I flew here, Google announced it was acquiring Nest, a luxury thermostat maker. I never thought I would use those two words together. Nest has sensors that detect who is in a room and when, so naturally there was concern that Google would now learn all this extra information about you, and know how hot your house is.</p>
<p>Google quickly deployed the Nest CEO, who promised that there would be safeguards and a privacy policy, and all kinds limits to make sure everything stayed kosher. And I have no reason to disbelieve the guy.</p>
<p>But I shouldn't need his word, or Google's corporate motto, or Magna Carta, or the <a href="http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/politics/treaty/the-treaty-in-brief">Treaty of Waitangi</a> to protect me from my thermostat. My old thermostat wasn't that scary! It was too dumb to snitch. And no one could hear it scream.</p>
<p>This new thermostat, on the other hand, has lawyers, PR people, a privacy policy, it's off writing blog posts somewhere, possibly eating my leftover pizza. It more like a sketchy roommate than a thermostat.</p>
<p>Let me make it clear what I'm worried about here. I'm not afraid of my appliances. I'm not afraid that Google is going to send me to the Googlag to mine bitcoins.</p>
<p>Nor am I afraid of a Greater New Zealand, grown drunk with electronic surveillance, aggressively expanding to control the Pacific Rim. That might be a nice change! If it happens, I will be waiting on the docks of San Francisco, bearing a basket of avocados, ready to welcome our Kiwi overlords.</p>
<p>What I'm afraid of is the society we already live in. Where people like you and me, if we stay inside the lines, can enjoy lives of comfort and relative ease, but God help anyone who is declared out of bounds. Those people will feel the full might of the high-tech modern state.</p>
<p>Consider your neighbors across the Tasman, stewards of an empty continent, who have <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_Solution">set up internment camps in the remotest parts of the Pacific</a> for fear that a few thousand indigent people might come in on boats, take low-wage jobs, and thereby destroy their society.</p>
<p>Or the country I live in, where we have a bipartisan consensus that the only way to preserve our freedom is to fly remote controlled planes that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drone_attacks_in_Pakistan#Civilian_casualties">occasionally drop bombs on children</a>. It's <a href="http://classiclit.about.com/od/brotherskaramazov/a/aa_brothersqut.htm">straight out of Dostoevski</a>.</p>
<p>Except Dostoevski needed a doorstop of a book to grapple with the question: “Is it ever acceptable for innocents to suffer for the greater good?” And the Americans, a more practical people, have answered that in two words: “Of course!”</p>
<p>Erika Hall in <a href="http://www.webstock.org.nz/14/programme/presentations/#hall">her talk yesterday</a> wondered what Mao or Stalin could have done with the resources of the modern Internet. It's a good question. If you look at the history of the KGB or Stasi, they consumed enormous resources just maintaining and cross-referencing their mountains of paperwork. There's a throwaway line in Huxley's Brave New World where he mentions "800 cubic meters of card catalogs" in the eugenic baby factory. Imagine what Stalin could have done with a decent MySQL server.</p>
<p>We haven't seen yet what a truly bad government is capable of doing with modern information technology. What the good ones get up to is terrifying enough.</p>
<p>I'm not saying we can't have the fun next-generation Internet, where everyone wears stupid goggles and has profound conversations with their refrigerator. I'm just saying we can't slap it together like we've been doing so far and expect everything to work itself out.</p>
<p>The good news is, it's a design problem! You're all designers here - we can make it fun! We can build an Internet that's distributed, resilient, irritating to governments everywhere, and free in the best sense of the word, like we dreamed of in the 90's. But it will take effort and determination. It will mean scrapping permanent mass surveillance as a business model, which is going to hurt. It will mean pushing laws through a sclerotic legal system. There will have to be some nagging.</p>
<p>But if we don't design this Internet, if we just continue to build it out, then eventually it will attract some remarkable, visionary people. And we're not going to like them, and it's not going to matter.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can read the <a href="https://static.pinboard.in/webstock_2014.htm">full transcript</a> of the presentation (which actually is about the life of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A9on_Theremin">Lev Sergeyevich Termen</a>).</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-03-12 14:41:16</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>A short story about mass surveillance</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2014/02/13/a-story-about-mass-surveillance/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>So imagine you have a camera in your house. In your living room. A surveillance camera, like those you see in a metro station. In fact not just in your house (because hey, after all you are not that important), but in everyone's house. Image there is a surveillance camera on every living room. Creepy right? Would you just let it there staring and watching at you? Every movement you make in your own house? Well this is what is going on right now. No seriously. This is what is happening; but in the digital world. You see a physical camera is so easy to spot and get you frustrated. But on the digital world, which is as real as the physical one, the surveillance mechanisms are not so easy to spot.</p>
<p>So I'm having this camera in my living room watching every move I make. and the other day Maria, a friend of mine, comes for a cup of coffee in my house. She comes from another country, with different surveillance methods and she's surprised to see the camera. <em>"You know you have a camera in your house? Over there in that corner of the ceiling."</em>. There are plenty of ways I could react to this remark. The obvious one would be to look her finger and not where it's pointing, pretending there is nothing there. Or I could start yelling at her <em>"Oh, come on. I know you people, all you do is scare people off. There is no camera! Don't try to terrorize us"</em>. Another approach would be that I actually get scared, censor myself and act as "normal" as I can. You know just sit there quietly and open my tv. Because that's what normal people do, right? I don't want to look suspicious and draw any attention on me from whoever is behind this camera. Until of course I really believe this and become that man who watches tv all day doing nothing out of the ordinary. Or... I could just thank Maria for stating the obvious and start thinking about what we can do about it.</p>
<p>A couple of hours later George, another friend, joins our company. He is more into technology than the average people. Actually a lot more. You know, these people that you can watch for hours talking only with acronyms and unknown words. So the discussion comes up again at this disturbing surveillance thing and he points out that there is a way to protect myself. A technical way to hide and obfuscate my movements inside my house, so they can't see what I'm doing (or at least make their job a lot harder). Well again there are various ways I could react to this. I could deny taking any measures to protect myself because that would make me look suspicious. I'm not that important. Let them focus on those who have something to hide. Or I could claim that this is a political problem and the only solution would be a political one. No technical measures can help us, so I refuse even to bother about them. Or... I could just thank George for having the patience to educate me about these things, and yes I would acknowledge the fact that this is a political problem and in the long term the solution should be political. But in the meantime I'm going to make their job a hell of a lot difficult. I'm going to help everyone look suspicious.</p></content>
      <pubDate>2014-02-13 11:50:16</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Mozilla growing community (and reps)</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2013/10/30/mozilla-growing-community-and-reps/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/dougbelshaw/10136415166/"><img alt="champions of the web" src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3712/10136415166_51b1cfa6c0.jpg" /></a></p>
<p><br />
No more that a month ago, around 1800 Mozillians got together in 3 different locations around the globe for the <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Summit2013">Mozilla Summit</a>. It's a huge number and it's getting bigger. I don't consider myself a long-time Mozilla contributor (I started actively contributing about 3 years ago), but I was always close to the project. Close enough to know that we came a long way over the last couple of years.</p>
<p><em>We grew as a project.</em> Exploring new directions (<a href="https://webmaker.org/">Webmaker</a>, <a href="http://opennews.org/">Journalism</a>, <a href="http://openbadges.org/">Education</a>) and trying once again to save the Open Web building new cool products that people love to use (<a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/os/">Firefox OS</a>).</p>
<p><em>We grew as a community.</em> Last Summit (about 3 years ago) had around <a href="https://blog.lizardwrangler.com/2013/03/31/mozilla-summit/">600 participants</a>. Today <strong>we are a community of nearly 2000 Mozillians</strong>, both paid and volunteer contributors. And these two aspects are inseparable. None of these new adventures would have been possible without this rapid growth of the community.</p>
<p>There are many reasons for this, but one of the most important accelerators was the fact that we had <strong>contributors engagement on the ground</strong>. 2.5 years ago Mozilla Reps was born, a programme to empower people and give them the ability and the necessary means to engage with potential contributors, to build and support local communities, to inspire people and spread the word about Mozilla's mission.</p>
<p>I can still remember the time where the local communities where contributing almost exclusively on localization. Which is important of course, but doesn't help alone on shaping the future of Mozilla project in the way that it's happening today. <strong>We opened up contribution paths and opportunities</strong> that changed the nature of Mozilla project for ever.</p>
<p>It wasn't even that common for people to organize events back then, or get support. Today Reps are organizing (or helping other Mozillians organize) <a href="https://reps.mozilla.org/events/">events</a> in a rate of 3 events per day! We managed to streamline the budget and swag requests, resulting in awesome events, like <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2013/01/join-us-for-firefox-os-app-days/">Firefox OS App Days</a>. Something that would be impossible 3 years ago.</p>
<p>Today Mozilla Reps, <a href="https://reps.mozilla.org/people/">spread around the world</a>, are keep doing awesome community building work facing the challenge of keeping up to speed with the a vastly growing community. Always trying to inspire even more people, engage more contributors and serve Mozilla's mission for an Open Web.</p>
<p><br />
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/gen/9643441237/"><img alt="mozilla reps" src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7385/9643441237_00b4c8aff0.jpg" /></a></p></content>
      <pubDate>2013-10-30 13:27:03</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Kickstarting a static website with ember.js and handlebars.js</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2013/10/20/kickstarting-a-static-website-emberjs-handlebarsjs/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>Sometimes you want to build quickly a static website. No need for a backend or a static content generator. But you come to a point where you want to introduce some simple features and you get annoyed mostly because you have to duplicate things. You have the same footer copied on every page or you have a list of items (pages) and you wish you could have the same template for all of them and get these items serialized in some way (the only way: json).</p>
<p><a href="http://emberjs.com/">Ember.js</a> (which includes <a href="http://handlebarsjs.com/">handlebars.js</a>) can really come in handy in these situations. I started using it for the first time when I wanted to build a simple static website for archiving Athens Friday night bike rides, known as <a href="http://freedayride.gr/">freeday</a>. And since it proved to be the right choice I'm keep using it every time I want to design something similar.</p>
<p>So in order to minimize the time I spend kickstarting such a website, I pushed a few bits of code that can serve as a starting point. Just check the <a href="https://github.com/comzeradd/static-ember">repo</a> and see how it <a href="http://comzeradd.github.io/static-ember/">looks like</a>.</p>
<p>PS. Of course ember.js is much more than this. If you are interested for more see this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1QHrlFlaXdI">video</a> and then dive into the <a href="http://emberjs.com/guides/">documentation</a>.</p></content>
      <pubDate>2013-10-20 22:59:13</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Hacking Firefox OS Developer Phone</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2013/05/17/hacking-firefox-os-developer-phone/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><img src="geeksphone.png" alt="keon" class="txt" /> Probably you already know about <a href="http://www.geeksphone.com/">Geeksphone</a>'s Firefox OS Developer Phones. A couple of days ago I received mine (the Keon version) as a <a href="https://reps.mozilla.org/">Mozilla Rep</a> for testing and showcasing Firefox OS on upcoming events.</p>
<p>Keon comes with an old Firefox OS build, which means that it misses many cool features already landed on the current release branch (for instance most of the contacts import options), but also makes bug reporting difficult since you have to determine if a bug you’ve found has already been resolved before reporting it.</p>
<p>So with a little help from <a href="http://adamkalis.github.io/">(Flash)Fredy</a> here are some quick steps to get your Keon device updated :-)</p>
<p>Flash a new Firefox OS build</p>
<p>At Geeksphone forum you’ll find a <a href="http://forum.geeksphone.com/index.php?topic=4834">relevant thread</a> with unofficial recent builds and detailed guidelines on how to flash it on your device. Nothing else to add here, besides the fact that flashing a build comes with a certain amount of risk :-)</p>
<h2>Update Gaia</h2>
<p>If you are feeling less adventurous you could just update Firefox OS UI (<a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Gaia">Gaia</a>). The steps are really easy. Plug your device and run:</p>
<pre><code>git clone https://github.com/mozilla-b2g/gaia.git
git checkout v1-train
make reset-gaia
</code></pre>
<p>This will restart your device and when it comes back you’ll have the new Gaia.</p>
<h2>The tools you need</h2>
<p>In order for all the above steps to work you need adb, which stands for <a href="https://developer.android.com/tools/help/adb.html">Android Debug Bridge</a> and it’s a simple command line tool that helps you communicate with a connected Androd/Linux phone device.</p>
<p>Here are the steps needed to have adb working (at least on <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora</a>). First download the <a href="https://developer.android.com/sdk/index.html">SDK tools</a> from Android. Let’s assume that you uncompressed the archive on ~/android-sdk/.</p>
<pre><code>cd ~/android-sdk/tools
./android
</code></pre>
<p>Then you check to install the “Tools”, that would probably have a “Not Installed” status on your system. This will download and install everything you need under ~/android-sdk/platform-tools.</p>
<p><img alt="adb" src="adb.jpg" /></p>
<p>If you want to use adb from everywhere you have to add it on your system’s PATH. In this case:</p>
<pre><code>export PATH=$PATH:~/android-sdk/platform-tools
</code></pre>
<p>You can add this to your ~/.bash_profile for permanent effect.</p>
<p>One last step is to add a udev rule for the specific device. Running lsusb on a terminal gives you the vendor identifier. For Keon this is “05c6″. So you have to add the line below at /etc/udev/rules.d/51-android.rules</p>
<pre><code>SUBSYSTEM=="usb", ATTR{idVendor}=="05c6", MODE="0666", GROUP="plugdev"
</code></pre>
<p>and tell udev to re-read the rules:</p>
<pre><code>sudo udevadm control --reload-rules
</code></pre>
<p>If you did everything correctly then plug your Keon device and run:</p>
<pre><code>adb devices
</code></pre>
<p>You should see a line for keon.</p>
<h2>Hack</h2>
<p>If you are developing an Open Web App then you could just use Firefox OS Simulator to push it on the Keon device. See how <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2013/05/pushing-firefox-os-apps-to-the-geeksphone/">simple that is</a>. The only thing you’ll need for this to work is the udev rule above. You won’t need adb, since the simulator comes with it’s own copy.</p>
<p>If you want to hack around Gaia and the core apps, then just fork the code, do all the changes you want and use your repo to flash Gaia on the phone as described above.</p>
<p>Happy Hacking :-)</p>
<p><em>Important: Don’t ever choose to reset your phone to Factory defaults. It seems that currently you get stuck if you do it and the only way to undo it is by flashing a new build (I speak from experience :P).</em></p></content>
      <pubDate>2013-05-17 12:37:19</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Libre Graphics Meeting 2013</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2013/04/29/libre-graphics-meeting-2013/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/8659115880/"><img alt="open design" src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8100/8659115880_f3708afc66.jpg" /></a>
<div align="center"><em>"Fuck commitees, I believe in lunatics" ~ Tibor Kalman</em></div>
<br /></p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/8659179138/" target="_blank"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8122/8659179138_13bf29e8a8_q.jpg" class="txt" /></a> The <a href="http://libregraphicsmeeting.org/2013/"><strong>Libre Graphics Meeting</strong></a> (LGM) is an annual gathering for the discussion of free and open source software used for design, illustration, typography, lay-out, art, photography, publishing, cartography, animation and video.</p>
<p>For years I wanted to participate and this year I finally did it. I had a presentation about <a href="http://popcorn.webmaker.org/">Popcorn Maker</a> and how people can use it to remix videos and teach others how to be web makers.</p>
<p>Check out my full Popcorn Maker presentation below and the full <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/sets/72157633271119214/">photo album</a>.</p>
<iframe src="http://www.rvl.io/comzeradd/make-popcorn/embed" height="420" width="576" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" scrolling="no"></iframe>

<p><br /></p>
<p>On the front wall of the Medialab Prado (the host venue) there was a 15-meter wide LED facade displaying processing.js artworks. A special <a href="http://programalaplaza.medialab-prado.es/">online editor</a> was created for people to submit "code" for this installation. Below is my simple humble contribution (inspired by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H4Kgzn3tDQU">similar music scene</a> from a favorite movie :P). </p>
<pre><code>void setup() {
  size(192, 157); 
  background(0); 
  frameRate(7);

  noStroke();
  colorMode(HSB); //HSB mode to have beautiful random colors
}

void draw () {
  x = Math.round(random(192)/16);
  y = Math.round(random(160)/16);
  fill(random(255), 200, 200);
  rect(x*16, y*16, 16, 16);
}
</code></pre>
<p>See the video below for more cool creations.</p>
<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/64292342?portrait=0" height="310" width="550" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0"></iframe></content>
      <pubDate>2013-04-29 15:13:28</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Making is Learning (Hive Athens & more)</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2013/03/21/making-is-learning-hive-athens-more/"/>
      <content type="html"><blockquote>
<p>"If children have interest, then education happens" ~ Arthur Clarke</p>
</blockquote>
<p>First week of March was dedicated on teaching, learning and learning to teach :)</p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/8523352849/"><img alt="pop-up" src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8229/8523352849_6e903f2e07.jpg" /></a></p>
<p><strong>Hive Athens Pop-Up event</strong></p>
<p>We had the first Pop-Up event of <a href="http://hiveathens.org/">Hive Athens</a>. A great overall experience. See here the <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/sets/72157632897101432/detail/">photo album</a> and a <a href="http://vimeo.com/comzeradd/hiveathens-popup1">mashup video</a>.</p>
<p>Personally I dedicated most of my time helping the WWF workshop about the "Earth Hour", where Popcorn Maker was used to make some great videos, but I found the time to have a quick pass through all activities.</p>
<p>It was a crash test for both Hive and local Mozilla community and I think it went pretty well. The facilitators did a great job and we may succeeded on planting the seed for a new generation of webmakers :) </p>
<p>Most of the workshops worked really well. I have the feeling that there was an engagement problem with the most physical ones. The facilitators were actually making more things than the participants. Just a reminder for future events. Connecting the activities with the web really helps, since the kids are getting in the process of <em>creating something that would be out there in public for ever</em>.</p>
<p>Additionally I think that one of the most important things about these types of events is that you must make sure that the <em>kids will have the chance for following up with the activity</em>. For instance the kids that created a comic strip using Thimble can keep hacking on that when they get home, or try to tell another story with other tools or other means. The point is that <em>they got in the process of storytelling</em>, learning (and realizing) that we live in a read/right world. I don't think that this level of learning process took place (for instance) at the Lego Mindstorms workhsop, since it's almost impossible for the kids to take or just publish what they made and there is not an easy way for a follow up (Legos are expensive and there is no relevant community that can help them after the event).</p>
<p>My personal rules/advice for these learning activities would be: </p>
<ul>
<li>Open-Source. In the broader sense, not just about software itself. <em>Openness is about removing barriers</em>. If a kid has to buy some expensive equipment or software, or has to give away some privacy rights and agree to some commercial service "Terms of Use" in order to keep hacking with what he/she learned, then you have a barrier.</li>
<li>Web. All this process and all these activities are <em>not about Web per se, is about <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Learning/WebLiteracyStandard">Literacy</a></em>. Web has probably become the largest public resource and the almost de facto medium for telling stories and sharing them with the rest of the world. Tying these activities with the web help all the participants better understand that they can be more than a consumer. Having your side of the story public out there makes that clear. And just like Wikipedia, even the slightest contribution is making a difference.</li>
<li>Ability to follow up. Well... if you manage to keep the first two rules, this would be easier. Also don't do this alone. Find cultural and educational organizations in your area that already create content or have youth activities. Find relevant communities.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Training Days</strong></p>
<p>I don't have words to describe that :) 40 Reps for all around the world <a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/117312389370621956919/albums/5854744512187304609?banner=pwa">gathered in one place</a> to exchange ideas and gain experience on how to teach the web, organize similar events, inspire more mentors, etc. Great to meet all these energetic people in person. I surely now feel more confident on running more learning and webmaking activities. </p>
<p><a href="https://plus.google.com/photos/117312389370621956919/albums/5854744512187304609/5854745447613665746?banner=pwa"><img alt="training days" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-Vt1G6glwsv8/UUA79v9ZEdI/AAAAAAAAGTE/Wjb1riAAPWU/s969/IMG_2339.JPG" /></a></p>
<p><strong>British Council School Lab</strong></p>
<p>The final day we got the chance of testing our skills in another event at the British Council, where kids (at an age range of 12-17) were given the challenge of creating a video about a (scientific) topic using the web (and thus Popcorn Maker). It's amazing how kids can always find a way to surprise you and hack the whole process in to a more creative path :)</p>
<p><strong>Upcoming activities</strong></p>
<p>Following the momentum of these events we (the <a href="http://mozilla-greece.org">Greek Mozillians</a>) already started organizing the first Webmaker events during April. Just <a href="http://webmaker.org">join the movement</a> :)</p>
<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/62336537?portrait=0" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe></content>
      <pubDate>2013-03-21 18:30:48</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>FirefoxOSAppDays - hold your breath</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2012/12/10/firefoxosappdays-hold-your-breath/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><strong>Firefox OS Apps Days</strong> are coming... A series of events which will take place in <strong>~20 locations around the world</strong> during the <strong>last week of January</strong>.</p>
<p>But.. </p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/8258007623/"><img alt="first things first" src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8199/8258007623_4bc8fe4cbd_z.jpg" /></a></p>
<p>...on Saturday we had a taste of what these events will be about, since we organized a small hackathon at <a href="http://hackerspace.gr/">Athens Hackerspace</a>. Around 40 developers showed up, willing to learn about <strong>Mozilla's new effort to liberate the mobile ecosystem through Open Web Apps and Firefox OS</strong> and of course <strong>contribute to that cause</strong>.</p>
<p>Some observations and remarks from the event and the feedback we got: </p>
<ul>
<li>Most of the attendees already knew their way around web technologies and they realized why using them for mobile apps makes sense</li>
<li>Many people don't know that web apps are functional on Android <strong>today</strong> (or even <a href="status-hsgr.jpg">Desktop</a>) and really get impressed when they find out.</li>
<li>Android developers got interested on using web as a platform.</li>
<li>It seems that the 5h hacking session is not enough to create a super wow app, but enough time to have some prototypes and working code.</li>
<li>Lack of thorough documentation on some <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/WebAPI">WebAPIs</a> and on WebActivities. We really need to improve that.</li>
<li>We have to emphasize the fact that Firefox Marketplace is not just another mobile application ecosystem.</li>
<li>A 20% of people tend to register for the event and not attending. Need to remember that when setting a cap on registration.</li>
<li>The fact that we had several devices really helped during the hacking session for testing code.</li>
<li><a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2012/11/announcing-the-prototype-firefox-os-simulator/">Firefox OS Simulator</a> is awesome! It just needs support for touch events ;)</li>
<li>Maybe some mini talks during the hacking session for minor subjects would be nice (eg. <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Apps/Manifest">Manifest</a> walk through, WebActivites, more info on some specific Web APIs, intro to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Responsive_web_design">responsive design</a> principles, <a href="git-basics.png">git basics</a>).</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/8259015218/"><img alt="demo: mapwire overview" src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8358/8259015218_2759d2d771_z.jpg" /></a></p>
<p>So hold your breath people for the big event. It's less than 2 months away. Help us liberate the mobile ecosystem using open web technologies. The only requirement for participation will be just endless love for freedom and the web. <strong>Let's make history again in the same way we did with Firefox.</strong></p>
<p>(full photo album from the event: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/sets/72157632205640335/">here</a>)</p></content>
      <pubDate>2012-12-10 00:52:24</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>mozilla at fosscomm2012</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2012/05/17/mozilla-fosscomm/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><a href="http://serres.fosscomm.gr">Fosscomm</a>, the annual conference of the Greek Free Software community, took place last weekend and Mozilla had a big presence with talks and workshops the whole Sunday.</p>
<p><img src="moz.png" alt="mozilla" class="txt" /> Starting early in the morning, along with <a href="https://reps.mozilla.org/u/pierros/">Pierros</a>, we had the opportunity to talk about "<strong>Firefox on 2012</strong>" and the new features that are developed and will land sometime during this year. We started with a quick summary of the things that came on 2011, as a direct result of rapid release process, and then we got through all the cool new features that are about to come. See the <a href="/presentations/fosscomm2012-firefox%20on%202012.html">Presentation</a> and the <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2012/03/firefox-in-2011-firefox-plans-for-2012/">Firefox Roadmap</a>.</p>
<p>Right after this I had the opportunity to do a hands-on presentation of all the <strong>Firefox developer tools</strong>, that really help the productivity of a web developer (without any need of 3rd party add-ons). In a nutshell: <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/Using_the_Web_Console">Web Console</a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/Tools/Page_Inspector">Inspector</a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/Tools/Scratchpad">Scratchpad</a>, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en/Tools/Style_Editor">Style Editor</a>.</p>
<p>Right after it was <a href="https://reps.mozilla.org/u/fredy/">Fredy</a>'s turn to give a hands-on presentation. This time about <strong>Add-Ons</strong> and how you can use the <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/developers/builder">SDK Builder</a>. Nice in depth presentation.</p>
<p>Then we moved to the main conference room where Pierros and Fredy gave a speech about <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/b2g/">B2G</a>. Seems that a lot of people were aware (or at least fully aware) about this huge project. The presentation ended with a demo of <strong>B2G</strong> running on a smartphone, that really impressed the audience.</p>
<p>Back to the hands-on presentations with an <strong>Apps &amp; Marketplace</strong> overview by Pierros and Fredy. It was a good opportunity to clarify why web apps are important and <a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2012/03/html5-the-difference-between-an-app-and-a-page/">what's the dereference with simple web pages</a>. In the end there was a joint effort to create a web app for Wikipedia, which currently is under review on <a href="https://marketplace.mozilla.org/">Mozilla Marketplace</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.sealabs.net/seadog/">Giorgos</a> and me did a presentation about "<strong>Identity on the Web</strong>", talking mostly about BrowserID and what changes on the way we identify ourselves on the web sites we need to login or register. We did a quick demo using an <a href="http://theopenphotoproject.org/">OpenPhoto</a> instance and talked a lot about the technical aspects of it. See the <a href="/presentations/fosscomm2012-identity%20on%20the%20web.html">presentation</a> and especially the video on the last slide.</p>
<p>Last presentation by Giorgos, who did a nice motivating presentation of the <strong>WebDev workflow</strong> he's using on Mozilla, and which steps you have to do in order to contribute.</p>
<p>Then we moved to the workshop room, where we did a nearly 2h <strong>workshop on B2G</strong> and show in what areas any community member can contribute. I think it was a great overall  presence of Greek Mozillians, we had the chance to talk with many people, and hopefully we'll keep up on the same spirit :)</p></content>
      <pubDate>2012-05-17 14:20:36</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>MozCamp 2011 recap</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2011/11/16/mozcamp-2011-recap/"/>
      <content type="html"><p><img src="Mozcamp_2011.png" class="txt" /> This weekend the <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/EU_MozCamp_2011/">Mozcamp 2011</a> took place at Berlin. This was actually the first Mozilla event I participated and I really had a great time, meeting a lot of mozillians, exchanging ideas, talking about the future of the web we are to trying to build.</p>
<p>Some of the highlights of this Mozcamp:</p>
<p><strong>ReMo project</strong></p>
<p>Being a Mozilla Rep myself, I should start from this one. If you aren't already aware of what that is, go to the <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/ReMo">relevant wiki page</a> and dig around. The Mozcamp was a great chance to get more familiar with the <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/ReMo/SIGs">SIGs</a> (Special Interested Groups) inside Mozilla and of course socialize with other Mozilla Reps.</p>
<p><strong>Mozspaces</strong></p>
<p>This is fairly new (I think). It's an effort of <a href="https://etherpad.mozilla.org/mozspaces-usage">building spaces</a> all around the globe for Mozillians to meet and work together.</p>
<p><strong>Mozilla IT</strong></p>
<p>Wouldn't be nice if the Mozilla IT infrastructure was so open that community members could participate? Check out how you can do it on this <a href="http://people.mozilla.org/~mrz/blog/4.html">blog post</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Open Web Apps</strong></p>
<p>I've <a href="/2011/08/05/open-web-apps-its-not-just-the-future-its-also-cool/">written before</a> about that. In Mozcamp I had the chance to see the current state of <a href="https://apps.mozillalabs.com/">open web apps</a> and watch a live demo of the <a href="https://apps.mozillalabs.com/appdir/">apps place</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Boot to Gecko</strong> One of the hottest Mozilla <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/B2G">projects</a> right now. Many WebAPIs have already been implemented and we actually had the chance to see a live demo of phone/sms web apps. So.. <a href="http://arewemobileyet.com/">are we mobile yet?</a></p>
<p><strong>PDF.js</strong></p>
<p>Getting HTML5 technologies to their limits. I attended the presentation, and really got impressed by the work been <a href="https://github.com/mozilla/pdf.js">made so far</a>. It's good to know that Adobe Reader it's one of the <a href="https://www.csis.dk/en/csis/news/3321/">most vulnerable programmes</a> on the web.</p>
<p><strong>Developer engagement &amp; Browser ID</strong></p>
<p>Great talks by <a href="http://christianheilmann.com/">Christian Heilmann</a>, on how to become an ass kick public speaker (!) and on the current state of <a href="https://browserid.org/">browserid</a>. I learned about a cool tracking page of <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/events">Mozilla public speeches</a>, about the browserid <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Engagement/Developer_Engagement/BrowserIDPlan">future plans</a> and discovered a <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Identity/BrowserID/FieldGuide">detailed browserid guide</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Amo builder</strong></p>
<p>Finally a great discussion about the new Add-ons Builder (aka <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Jetpack">Jetpack</a>). It seems that the most difficult job there is to convience the old-school add-on developers about the neccessity of migrating to Jetpack. Some benefits: Easier coding (you don't need to know much about XUL), Restartless add-ons, Firefox version independent. <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/developers/">Get a ride</a>.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/6347861402/"><img alt="q&amp;a" src="https://farm7.static.flickr.com/6106/6347861402_3082969cf8.jpg" /></a> more photos: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/sets/72157628134486968/">mozcamp album</a></p></content>
      <pubDate>2011-11-16 11:07:03</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Open Web Apps, it's not just the future, it's also cool.</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2011/08/05/open-web-apps-its-not-just-the-future-its-also-cool/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>If you're following news about web technologies, and not living in a cave, you'd probably heard about <a href="https://apps.mozillalabs.com/">Open Web Apps</a>. An initiative of <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/">Mozilla Foundation</a>.</p>
<p>I could try to prove why this is this the future, but currently I'd like to show you how cool this future is. Let's call this a glimpse of the future.</p>
<p>First of all install the web app <a href="https://people.mozilla.com/~anarayanan/openwebapps_bundle_0.3.xpi">add-on</a>. Now go to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/">New York Times</a> website. You'll see a notification that this site has a web app. All you have to do is choose to install it. This will create a nytimes app tab on your firefox and a whole new experience on navigating to the newspaper.</p>
<p><img alt="nytimes" src="nytimes.jpg" /></p>
<p>This specific web app is taking advantage of touch gestures, so try it on your tablet as well.</p>
<p>So here is a cool thing, we discover along with <a href="http://pierros.papadeas.gr/">Pierros</a>. If you have a tablet that doesn't still support open web apps (nudge nudge say no more) you can still test this one. All you have to do is find the correct url. This web app doesn't manfest an address bar (because it doesn't need one) so type:</p>
<p><code>about:apps</code></p>
<p><img alt="about:apps" src="aboutapps.jpg" /></p>
<p>select "View Manifest" and spot the "launch_path".</p>
<p><img alt="appmanifest" src="appmanifest.jpg" /></p>
<p>So go to your tablet and type: <a href="http://nytimes.com/skimmer/">http://nytimes.com/skimmer/</a>. Enjoy :)</p></content>
      <pubDate>2011-08-05 00:16:24</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>speed up firefox (reloaded)</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2010/06/23/speed-up-firefox-reloaded/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>I've posted before about<a href="/2009/04/23/speed-firefox/"> this little hack on speeding up firefox</a>. The key is that you actually <strong>move the entire .mozilla folder from disk to memory</strong>. First you have to mount /tmp to memory (some linux distributions may do this by default) adding this line to /etc/fstab and rebooting:</p>
<p><code>none /tmp tmpfs size=512M,nr_inodes=200k,mode=01777 0 0</code></p>
<p>Then it's safe to do:</p>
<pre><code>cp -R /home/user/.mozilla /home/user/.mozilla_save
mv /home/user/.mozilla /tmp/mozilla
ln -s /tmp/mozilla /home/user/.mozilla
</code></pre>
<p>I updated the script so I can use it as a system init script:</p>
<pre><code>#!/bin/bash

start() {
    mkdir -p /tmp/mozilla
    rsync -avi --delete /home/user/.mozilla_save/ /home/user/.mozilla/
}

stop() {
    size=`du -xs /home/user/.mozilla/ | awk '{print $1}'`
    digits=`expr length $size`
    if [ $digits -gt 4 ]; then
        rsync -avi --delete /home/user/.mozilla/ /home/user/.mozilla_save/
    else
        echo 'no!'
        exit 0
    fi
}

case "$1" in
start)
     start
     ;;
stop)
     stop
     ;;
*)
     echo $"Usage: $0 {start|stop}"
     exit 1;;
esac
</code></pre>
<p>So I placed this script at /etc/init.d/, made it executable and created a link inside /etc/rc.5/</p>
<p><code>ln -s /etc/init.d/ffsync.sh /etc/rc5.d/S99ffsync</code></p>
<p>rc5 because the default runlevel on Fedora is 5. You can see yours from /etc/inittab. So every time my system boots the above script runs with the start option (executing the start function) and every time it halts/reboots it runs with the stop option (stop function). In order to be sure that no data loss will occur in the unlikely event of sudden shutdown, I have a cronjob that saves the mozilla folder every 15 minutes.</p>
<p><code>*/15 * * * * /etc/init.d/ffsync.sh stop</code></p>
<p>Trust me. With the above hack you'll see <strong>a significant difference on firefox's speed</strong>. Especially if you're you using <a href="http://blog.mozilla.com/blog/2008/04/21/a-little-something-awesome-about-firefox-3/">firefox's awesome address bar</a> to search through your browser's history.</p></content>
      <pubDate>2010-06-23 14:30:06</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>speed up firefox</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2009/04/23/speed-firefox/"/>
      <content type="html"><p>firefox 3 features <a href="http://support.mozilla.com/en-US/kb/Smart+Location+Bar">an awesome address</a> bar that helps you search through your history (and bookmarks) by just typing a word or phrase that's part of either the url or the title. the problem is that if you keep the browsing history for a long time (lime me) the address bar search process becomes very slow. a cool solution is to place the ~/.mozilla folder on ram (which is a lot faster than disk). i already have /tmp on ram, so i made a symbolic link ~/.mozilla pointing to /tmp/mozilla. and then i use the script below in order to save/restore the contents of mozilla folder: </p>
<pre><code>#!/bin/bash

if [ $# -lt 1 ]; then
    echo "usage: ff_sync.sh save/restore"
    exit 0
fi

action=$1

if [ "$action" = "save" ]; then
    size=`du -xs /home/user/.mozilla/ | awk '{print $1}'`
    digits=`expr length $size`
    if [ $digits -gt 4 ]; then
        rsync -avi --delete /home/user/.mozilla/ /home/user/.mozilla_save/
    else
        echo 'no!'
        exit 0
    fi
fi

if [ "$action" = "restore" ]; then
    mkdir -p /tmp/mozilla\
    rsync -avi --delete /home/user/.mozilla_save/ /home/user/.mozilla/
fi
</code></pre>
<p>all i have to do is run this script with the appropriate option when booting/halting the pc. on gentoo you have /etc/conf.d/local.start and /etc/conf.d/local.stop for this kind of things. and i have to say that i'm really impressed. firefox speed  improved amazingly. and i mean firefox overall speed, not just the address bar ;)</p></content>
      <pubDate>2009-04-23 11:48:38</pubDate>
    </entry>
  
</feed>