<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>Nikos Roussos</author>
  <title>nikos.roussos - life</title>
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/" />
  <icon>https://www.roussos.cc/favicon.ico</icon>
  <logo>https://www.roussos.cc/static/img/</logo>
  <updated>2018-03-02T00:32:41Z</updated>
  
    <entry>
      <title>do something</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2018/01/05/do-something/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p><img alt="unequalscenes" src="/2018/01/05/do-something/unequalscenes.jpg" />
<small><em>Image credit: Johnny Miller, "Unequal Scenes"</em></small>
<br><br></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Αν αποφασίσεις το που θες να εργάζεσαι με βάση το πως πληρώνεσαι,  τότε είναι πολύ πιθανόν να συμμετέχεις στην διαμόρφωση ενός κοινού μας  μέλλοντος όπως το οραματίζεται μια πολύ μικρή μειοψηφία του παγκόσμιου  πληθυσμού. Συνεισφέρουν τα αποτελέσματα της δουλειάς σου στη διαμόρφωση  ενός μέλλοντος που ΕΣΥ οραματίζεσαι;" ~ Pawel Stanczyk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Είναι δύσκολο να αντιληφθείς αυτό που σε περικλείει όταν είσαι μέρος  του. Είναι δύσκολο να αποστασιοποιηθείς όταν είσαι πολύ κοντά. Μια  νοητική άσκηση που προτείνουν οι δάσκαλοι και οι σοφοί της αρετής είναι  αυτή της εξωγήινης παρατήρησης.</p>
<p>Φαντάσου πως είσαι μέρος μιας  εξωγήινης αποστολής που επισκέπτεται τη γη. Πριν κάνετε την πρώτη επαφή  έχετε μείνει σε τροχιά γύρω απ’ αυτόν τον περίεργο μπλε πλανήτη και τον  παρατηρείτε. Πώς θα ξέρεις που πρέπει να προσεδαφιστείς; Που είναι το  “κέντρο” του ανθρώπινου πολιτισμού, αν δεν τον παρατηρήσεις πρώτα;</p>
<p>Αναλογίσου  λίγο αυτή την κατάσταση. Αναλογίσου να παρατηρείς ανθρώπους να  σπαταλούν την ενέργεια τους, τον χρόνο τους, την ευφυΐα τους (ατομική  και συλλογική) σε έργα και δράσεις που δεν παράγουν τίποτα στο τέλος  πέρα απ’ την αέναη ανατροφοδότηση και συντήρηση του τρόπου ζωής μιας  πολύ μικρής μειονότητας.
<br><br></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Αν οι μηχανές παράγουν όλα όσα χρειαζόμαστε, το μέλλον μας εξαρτάται  απ’ το πως θα τα διανέμουμε. Όλοι θα μπορούν να απολαύσουν μια πολυτελή  ζωή αν ο πλούτος που θα παράγουν οι μηχανές διαμοιράζεται, ή εναλλακτικά  οι περισσότεροι άνθρωποι θα καταλήξουν απελπιστικά φτωχοί αν οι  ιδιοκτήτες των μηχανών ενωθούν κατά της διανομής του πλούτου. Μέχρι τώρα  η κυρίαρχη τάση φαίνεται να είναι η δεύτερη, με την τεχνολογία να  οδηγεί στην όλο και αυξανόμενη ανισότητα." ~ Stephen Hawking</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Έλα τώρα ξανά στη γη. Άσε αυτό το νοητικό πείραμα πίσω σου και γίνε άνθρωπος ξανά. Tώρα που έχεις αποκτήσει μια καλύτερη προοπτική της κατάστασης σου, πραγματοποίησε το δεύτερο πείραμα. Σκέψου πως λόγω κάποιας περίεργης διαβολικής σύμπτωσης σκοντάφτεις πάνω σε έναν θησαυρό. Το βασικό στοιχείο εδώ είναι πως αυτό το ατύχημα σου έχει αυτομάτως λύσει το οικονομικό σου πρόβλημα. Δεν χρειάζεται να σε απασχολήσει ποτέ ξανά αυτό το θέμα για όσο ζεις. Τι θα έκανες;</p>
<p>Ξέρω ανθρώπους που απλά θα συνέχιζαν σαν να μην έχει αλλάξει τίποτα, θα συνέχιζαν να εκπλήσσουν τους εξωγήινους φίλους μας τόσο πολύ που ίσως να έβαζαν πορεία για άλλο πλανήτη. Ξέρω ανθρώπους που θα σάστιζαν που δεν θα ήξεραν τι να κάνουν, και που βαθιά μέσα τους θα ένιωθαν πως τους έχει δοθεί μια ανέλπιστη ευκαιρία. Ξέρω ανθρώπους που είναι έτοιμοι από καιρό, που θα έβρισκαν επιτέλους αυτό τον χαμένο χρόνο για να λύσουν όλα τα δύσκολα προβλήματα που τους βασανίζουν το μυαλό και τους κρατάνε άγρυπνους χρόνια τώρα.
<br><br></p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ποιο είναι πιο σημαντικό πράγμα στον κόσμο πάνω στο οποίο θα μπορούσες να δουλεύεις αυτή τη στιγμή; ...Κι αν δεν δουλεύεις πάνω σ’ αυτό, γιατί όχι;" ~ Aaron Swartz</p>
</blockquote>
<p><small><em>(όπως δημοσιεύτηκε στο <a href="http://chimeres.gr/zine">36ο τεύχος</a> του fanzine chimeres)</em></small></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2018-01-05 12:57:00</published>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>My Cold Brew recipe</title>
      <link href="https://www.roussos.cc/2016/10/23/cold-brew/"/>
      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>Cold brew is my favorite type of iced coffee. In the spirit of diy I usually brew my own homemade stuff. And in the spirit of open sourcing everything I thought it would be nice to document my personal "recipe".</p>
<p>Searching around you'll find many different ways of making cold brew and the truth is that there is no right or wrong way of doing it (well... except some very wrong ways of doing it). This kind of brewing is fairly new and different people follow different rules. Especially when it comes to the coffee-water ratio. You should experiment with different ratios and find what's more suitable to you, in terms of flavor and caffeine amount. This is just what tastes good for me.</p>
<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/30428064031/in/album-72157675593290325/" title="Coffee"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5498/30428064031_55ed0981ac_c.jpg" width="800" height="534" alt="Coffee"></a></p>
<h4><strong>Coffee Grind</strong></h4>
<p>You need coarsely ground coffee. More coarse than you'd grind for filter coffee. If you have your own grinder you should be able to achieve that easily. I avoid brewing more than 100g each time. Otherwise I'd need a really big bottle to store it when it's ready. So use your scale wisely. Depending on the kind of bottles or jars you have (and your fridge can hold) you may end up with a different amount of coffee to use. You'll have a better way of deciding this by the time you end up reading this post.</p>
<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/30514622495/in/album-72157675593290325/" title="Weight"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5700/30514622495_92e5f2468f_c.jpg" width="800" height="520" alt="Weight"></a></p>
<h4><strong>Brew Process</strong></h4>
<p>I use a jar for that. One with a cap to cover it and keep unwanted smells outside. My volume ratio is 1-4. That means 1 part of coffee and 4 parts of water. I don't measure water, I know the jar's total volume so I can do it visually. If you want to be precise (I'm not), you should know the exact volume of your jar and the fact that roasted coffee's density is around 432kg/m<sup>3</sup>.</p>
<p>So fill in water and stir it good. You can find alternative ways for that specific part. Some people enclose the coffee inside filters or other kind of pouches, so they can remove it easily later. I prefer to filter afterwards, avoiding any other material to be part in this process and let the coffee brew directly within water.</p>
<p>You can either leave it on room temperature for 12h or put in the fridge for the next 24h. I prefer the latter, slowing down the brewing process. It's important to stir the coffee another 2-3 times during these 24 hours.</p>
<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/30427946381/in/album-72157675593290325/" title="Jar"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8567/30427946381_d74d80424a_c.jpg" width="800" height="511" alt="Jar"></a></p>
<h4><strong>Filtering</strong></h4>
<p>I filter directly to a bottle, using a filter paper (like the ones I'd use for filter coffee machine) and a funnel to make sure I don't miss a drop. If you don't have filter papers, you can use a wet napkin that you wrung before using it, but the filtering process will be slower.</p>
<p>Once you filter it all, you store the bottle inside your fridge again.</p>
<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/30514700775/in/album-72157675593290325/" title="Filtering"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5781/30514700775_03a59e2c74_c.jpg" width="800" height="534" alt="Filtering"></a></p>
<h4><strong>Enjoy</strong></h4>
<p>Cold brew is a lot more caffeinated than your regular espresso or other forms of iced coffee. That's why you should dilute down your cold brew with water. My ratio is around 1-4 again. Cold brew is served cold (I know, right?). That means you can use a lot of ice cubes and a bit less water. Usually I don't like milk in my coffee, but cold brew is an exception. Milk bonds really well, and you can use it instead of adding water (or use both).</p>
<p>The result is a nice coffee drink, less acidic and full of flavors compared to other forms of iced coffee, and a long lasting taste of pride for brewing your own coffee.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/comzeradd/30398329052/in/album-72157675593290325/" title="Enjoy"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5727/30398329052_38eff01593_c.jpg" width="800" height="534" alt="Enjoy"></a></p>
<hr>

<p><em>Comments and reactions on <a href="https://librenet.gr/posts/601875">Diaspora</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/comzeradd/status/698135511437803520">Twitter</a></em></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
      <published>2016-10-23 21:31:00</published>
    </entry>
  
</feed>